<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://lellep.xyz/blog/</id><updated>2017-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Turbulence simulation data in real-life</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/turbulence-simulation-data-in-real-life.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-12-19:/blog/turbulence-simulation-data-in-real-life.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;3D print and resin cast of a turbulent flow from 3D simulation&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Amongst others, I developed a code for simulating Newtonian fluids such as water
during my Master studies. Choosing proper settings, one can easily generate large
amounts of 3D data that resembles a turbulent flow in a&amp;nbsp;box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A snapshot of this data was captured and 3D printed. From that, a silicone mould was
made and used to cast a resin version of the simulation&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I am able to hold my abstract experiments from my studies in Theoretical
Physics in my own hands. It took a long way from performing the simulation on a
powerful super computer to creating a real-life silicone mould with which the data
can be&amp;nbsp;casted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps that I performed are the following&amp;nbsp;ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate the turbulent data in a channel flow geometry. The boundary conditions
are periodic in spanwise and streamwise directions. The wall-normal direction
uses free-slip boundary&amp;nbsp;conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is exported to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VTR&lt;/span&gt; format which is read by ParaView. From there,
it is exported as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt;. ParaView is used to find a nice iso surface in the
time&amp;nbsp;series.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The raw simulation data is post-processed in Blender to generate a file
that can be 3D&amp;nbsp;printed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The post-processed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; is 3D&amp;nbsp;printed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 3D print is sanded and subsequently coated with a fill primer to hide the
3D print specific layer&amp;nbsp;structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A silicone mould is made from the 3D print which is finally used for the resin&amp;nbsp;cast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video visualizes the simulation from which the 3D printed data is taken.
The flow in the simulation box is color
coded where red values are large positive values in the flow  direction and blue values are large negative
values in the flow direction. The flow direction is the x coordinate. The gray surface at t=0 is the one
that is 3D printed and resin casted here. The video shows the turbulent evolution of that surface in&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/videos/turbulentDataCast/turbulence_isosurfaces.mp4"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/turbulence_isosurfaces_frontPic.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The simulation data that has been used for the&amp;nbsp;cast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is a mp4 file and can either be downloaded or viewed directly in the&amp;nbsp;browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-outcome"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;outcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, the result of the cast is shown: It is the transparent piece which took
two days to cure inside the silicone&amp;nbsp;mould.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/0_3d_prints.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;3D prints in two sizes, colors and&amp;nbsp;resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/1_mould_box.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;3D print with white fill primer inside its silicone moulding&amp;nbsp;box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/2_silicone_mould.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Silicone&amp;nbsp;mould.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/3_resin_cast.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Resin cast and its&amp;nbsp;template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-details"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is acquired by running the simulation that I wrote for a sufficiently
long time in the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations&amp;#8217; turbulent regime at
Re=400. My simulation is based on a pseudo-spectral algorithm so that one
can reconstruct the full velocity fields from the spectral expansion coefficients
at arbitrary spatial resolutions. The fields are reconstructed and
saved as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VTR&lt;/span&gt; files (using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/pauloh/pyevtk"&gt;PyEVTK&lt;/a&gt;).
These can be opened in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.paraview.org/"&gt;ParaView&lt;/a&gt; to study how
the fields evolve over time. After deciding upon one flow field and
one of its iso surfaces, the spectral coefficients are used to generate a very
high-resolution spatial field. This data is saved as a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; file is post-processed in Blender: The 2D iso surface is extruded
downwards to obtain a true 3D structure that can be 3D printed. Furthermore,
small artifacts or structures that are hard to 3D print are&amp;nbsp;removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model is 3D printed in black &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;. I tested multiple sizes and multiple vertical resolutions
on an UltiMaker 3. After holding all the 3D prints in my hand I decided to pick
the highest vertical resolution of 0.1mm and a size of 9mm x 6mm x 3mm. This
model is sanded down and white fill primer is applied to hide the vertical layers. It turns out
that this last step reduces the visible vertical layers very well.
That procedure might be an alternative to using an acetone bath for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ABS&lt;/span&gt; in
case &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ABS&lt;/span&gt; cannot be used but a smooth surface is necessary,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A silicone mould is made in a small paper box. Using release spray is recommended
to avoid the destruction of the silicone mould while removing the 3D print. Spending some
time to prepare the 3D print is suggested to polish its look and feel because
the silicone will capture all its details for all the following resin casts to&amp;nbsp;create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This silicone mould is finally used for a resin cast. One can use the silione
mould many times. The casting should be done in a well ventilated room, believe&amp;nbsp;me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="acknowledgements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ucreatestudio.is.ed.ac.uk/"&gt;uCreate Studio from the University of Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt;  which enabled me to
test multiple prototypes of the 3D print in various sizes and resolutions.
Thanks to their Mike Boyd for ideas on how to realize this project.
This place is truely exceptional and an amazing opportunity for students
to learn anything! I believe the uCreate Studio is a concept that needs to be copied
from universities across the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="3D Printing"></category><category term="Fluid Dynamics"></category><category term="Edinburgh"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning a Neural Network with Genetic Algorithms</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/learning-a-neural-network-with-genetic-algorithms.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-11-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-11-25:/blog/learning-a-neural-network-with-genetic-algorithms.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Numerical experiment combining neuroevolution and an old &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SEGA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;game.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Genetic algorithms can be used to optimize complex problems by using
techniques that ressemble genetic evolution. One such complex problem can be the
learning process of a neural network: Using genetic algorithms for this purpose
is referred to as&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;Neuroevolution&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across nice projects that use genetic algorithms to learn neural networks
that controll the behaviour of some agents in a simplified&amp;nbsp;world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arithmetic snake searching for food: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBLJFYr7zB8"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBLJFYr7zB8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flappy Bird scoring points: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L6bbFgjkqK0"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L6bbFgjkqK0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Car driving along a track: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5lJuEW-5vr8"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5lJuEW-5vr8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-project"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working on a discrete version of &amp;#8220;Frogger&amp;#8221; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frogger"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frogger&lt;/a&gt;)
that is controlled by a neural network which is learned through a genetic&amp;nbsp;algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this project, I am covering a few other aspects as&amp;nbsp;well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn C++: The project is developed in C++. The development speed might not be as
high as when developed in Python but in return I will learn object-oriented programming
in C++, the compilation tool-chain and modern C++ standards such as&amp;nbsp;2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neural network topologies: The concepts of neural networks and their topology is
part of this project as I implement the neural network from scratch. This is
particularly simple in this case because only forward evaluations are&amp;nbsp;required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artificial simplified world and agent-based learning: The idea of individuals who
live in a simplified world and respond to their environment seems like an exciting
numerical experiment to&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-code"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code can be found here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/Mc_M/neuroevolution_crossroad"&gt;https://bitbucket.org/Mc_M/neuroevolution_crossroad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="resources"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genetic algorithms: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_algorithm"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_algorithm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neuroevolution: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuroevolution"&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuroevolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="AI"></category><category term="Edinburgh"></category></entry><entry><title>Greasing the groove: Push ups - Results</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups-results.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-29T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T23:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-05-29:/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups-results.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Results of 120 push ups for 30&amp;nbsp;days.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did 120 push ups, 6 times 20 repetitions spread arbitrarily over the day, for 30 days
starting the 04/24/2017. The last of these workouts has been done the 23rd of May 2017 without
skipping any repetition during the 30 days. After all, I performed 3600 push&amp;nbsp;ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the 29th of May 2017, I measured my maximal number of push ups anew. Initially, I performed
42 with 20 warming up&amp;nbsp;repetitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time without warming up repetitions, I performed 70 push ups. This is a performance I am
happy&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="experiences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experiences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After approximately 15 days into the challenge, I felt that my handstand and overall
shoulder strength increased. Exercices such as holding a frog position without leaning on my knees
became more accessible and the initial phase of a straddle press felt like I could make future progress
with. In comparison to my pull up challenge of 50 pull ups a day for 30 days in the winter 2015/2016,
this challenge has not had an as big impact on my daily life in terms of soreness and time consumption.
However, also the performance increase hasn&amp;#8217;t been as dramatic. Generally, one should make sure that the
excercise performed in such a challenge is not too difficult as the body will struggle even with the
simplest excercises when repeated that often. While I underestimated that for the past
pull up challenge, I did take this into account for the just finished push up challenge. Getting the 6
sets done over a day was relatively easy so that one could think of performing more than 6 sets. I
did the repetitions exclusively on parallets which (a) protected my wrists and (b) increased the range of
motion. My wrists never made any problems and, amazingly, I got used to the increased range of motion
so that regular flat-hand push ups feel easy now. While the wrists were fine throughout the challenge,
my shoulder felt irritated sometimes. However, never to the degree of pain but mostly only&amp;nbsp;cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="outlook"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various future challanges came to my&amp;nbsp;mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3x 50 push up repetitions a day: For increasing the maximal number. 20 repetitions were too easy
after some&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;L sit to tucked press (explained in terms of the frog position above). I might train these excercises
separately at first to build up enough strength for the&amp;nbsp;challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frog stand on&amp;nbsp;parallets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stretching routine each&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stretching routine seems the most appealing for me now as it is more passive after such an active&amp;nbsp;challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Sports"></category></entry><entry><title>Greasing the groove: Push ups</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-23T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-04-23T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-04-23:/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Application of &amp;#8220;greasing the groove&amp;#8221; training method to push&amp;nbsp;ups.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I apply the training method &amp;#8220;Greasing the groove&amp;#8221; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#gtg" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; to my push up performance.
My interpretation of this method&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not train the excercise to&amp;nbsp;fatigue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train the excercise very&amp;nbsp;frequently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application to push ups means in this case for&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the maximal performance. Performance is measured as number of
proper-form push ups. To relax my wrists and increase the range of motion, I use my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt;
parallets or knuckles if no parallets are available. &lt;strong&gt;Result&lt;/strong&gt;:
42 push ups after a warm up set of 20&amp;nbsp;repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform half of the maximal performance - 20 in my case at the time being -
six times each day for 30 days. I determined the set number of six by available
time each day, integration in my other physical training and exhaustion. The number of
sets should be distributed equally over the day and are possibly integrated in other training
occasions. The equal distribution includes working times and time at&amp;nbsp;home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this study&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase push up performance. While push ups are an essential excercise, I found
them surprisingly exhausting. I had very good experience with 50 (ring) pull ups
each day for 30 days for my pull up performance in winter&amp;nbsp;2015/2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase overall push performance. This will help for more complex composite movements
that I am weak&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a better push up&amp;nbsp;form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start date is tomorrow, &lt;strong&gt;04/24/2017&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;#8220;We are what we repeatedly do. Excellence, then, is not an act, but a habit.&amp;#8221; (Will Durant)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="gtg" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Further reading can be found here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.100pushups.com/greasing-the-groove/"&gt;http://www.100pushups.com/greasing-the-groove/&lt;/a&gt;.
No guarantee on correctness but a good read.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="Sports"></category></entry></feed>