<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog - languages</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/feeds/languages.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://lellep.xyz/blog/</id><updated>2019-09-14T10:46:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>by Martin Lellep</subtitle><entry><title>Phone in foreign language</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/phone-in-foreign-language.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-14T10:46:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-14T10:46:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2019-09-14:/blog/phone-in-foreign-language.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;My experiences with using my phone in Russian for 1&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In around August 2018, I switched my phone&amp;#8217;s language from English to Russian. I switched it back to English mid-September of this year&amp;nbsp;(2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of switching my phone to Russian arose from the desire to expose myself to the Russian language more authentically in daily life. As my phone is my daily fellow, using it in Russian suggested&amp;nbsp;itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a vacation in an Eastern Russians-speaking country in September 2019, I came to the conclusion that this strategy is suboptimal at this point in time. These are the major three reasons why I decided to switch it back, sorted according to their&amp;nbsp;importance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My level of Russian is admittedly not high enough to make practical use of this daily authentic&amp;nbsp;exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Studying Russian at an beginner-ish level, adhering to text books seems to be a more efficient solution. The latter approach appears to be a denser and more explicit learning experience. Despite its lack of authenticity, it is probably more efficient at the beginning of learning a&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The phone&amp;#8217;s usability is severely crippled if one does not honestly attempt to learn all the new words one is exposed&amp;nbsp;to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to conclude by encouraging you, fellow language learners, to try it out in your target language! It is indeed very authentic and learning through this approach by the mechanism of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osmosis"&gt;osmosis&lt;/a&gt; did work for me. I haven&amp;#8217;t learned as many new words as I wanted to but this is solely due to me being not consistent enough and now having a high enough skill level in Russian, yet. In the future, I will certainly set my phone back to Russian&amp;nbsp;again!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="languages"></category></entry><entry><title>Exporting Anki statistics manually</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/exporting-anki-statistics-manually.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-29T20:14:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-29T20:14:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2018-09-29:/blog/exporting-anki-statistics-manually.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A description of how to export Anki statistics by directly hacking the Anki desktop&amp;nbsp;client.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order to document what I was able to achieve while &lt;a class="reference external" href="{filename}/ignored/Qualitative/learning_Italian_for_30_days.rst"&gt;learning Italian for one month&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to be able to export my Anki statistics to a data format that could be processed and plotted manually. It turns out that there is no feature in the Anki desktop client that enables the easy export of the computed statistics data that is shown on the statistics&amp;nbsp;page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I found a hack-ish workaround by tweaking the original Anki code that computes the statistics in order to export the data myself. This article is a quick explanation of how to export the statistics that is generated by&amp;nbsp;Anki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we&amp;nbsp;go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Find the Anki installation by typing &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;whereis anki&lt;/tt&gt; in your Linux terminal. My output&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
$ whereis anki
anki: /usr/bin/anki /usr/share/anki /usr/share/man/man1/anki.1.gz
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checking these paths reveals that &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/usr/share/anki&lt;/tt&gt; is the path that contains the source files of the Anki desktop client. These files are written in Python. Therefore, it is easy to modify&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Within &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/usr/share/anki&lt;/tt&gt;, the file &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/usr/share/anki/anki/stats.py&lt;/tt&gt; contains all the code that computes the statistics and outputs the data to the corresponding window of the Anki desktop&amp;nbsp;client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The code in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;stats.py&lt;/tt&gt; is self-explanatory and can be modified to one&amp;#8217;s liking. Let me state one example here: The method &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;dueGraph()&lt;/tt&gt; is modified to export the statistics data that it computes anyway. It should be denoted at that point that Anki informs you about errors if erroneous code has been added to any function - that makes debugging your added code quite comfortable. The code is changed as&amp;nbsp;follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
# Original version
def dueGraph(self):
    ...
    txt += self._dueInfo(tot, len(totd)*chunk)
    return txt

# Hacked version
def dueGraph(self):
    ...
    txt += self._dueInfo(tot, len(totd)*chunk)
    # &amp;lt;&amp;lt; Start of new code
    import os
    with open(os.path.join('/home/&amp;lt;user&amp;gt;', 'dueGraph.dat'), 'a') as f:
        f.write(json.dumps(data, indent=4))
    # End of new code &amp;gt;&amp;gt;
    return txt
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The additional code block creates a file &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;/home/&amp;lt;user&amp;gt;/dueGraph.dat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; where &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;user&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt; must be replaced by your username. This file contains the data that is used to generate the plot called &amp;#8220;Forecast&amp;#8221; in the statistics&amp;nbsp;window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The original plot called &amp;#8220;Forecast&amp;#8221; is shown&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/export_Anki_statistics_manually/forecast_default_plot.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/export_Anki_statistics_manually/forecast_default_plot.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The original figure &amp;#8220;Forecast&amp;#8221; from the stats report generated by the Anki desktop&amp;nbsp;client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The data that is written to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;/home/&amp;lt;user&amp;gt;/dueGraph.dat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; can be used easily to generate a plot that is to your liking based on the underlying data. That is shown in the following figure. This figure has been generated with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/plot_dueGraph.py"&gt;simple Python&lt;/a&gt; script using matplotlib and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/dueGraph.dat"&gt;the exported data of my Anki deck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/export_Anki_statistics_manually/forecast_custom_plot.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/export_Anki_statistics_manually/forecast_custom_plot.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The underlying data is used to generate a custom&amp;nbsp;figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;We are&amp;nbsp;done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concluding, it is possible to adapt the original Anki source code to export the statistics data manually, which, ultimately, enables one to create custom plots around that data. While the above procedure shows how already computed data is exported, own statistics based on the raw data in the Anki database could be computed and exported as well. However, attention must be brought to the fact that the plotted data of the above two figures appears &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to be the same. I was not able to spot any mistakes from my side or apparent code passages that modify the data after I save it manually in the Anki source&amp;nbsp;code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this article shows that exporting the data is a straightforward process but caution is advised when using the data without any prior&amp;nbsp;inspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kudos go to Leonard Salewski for his valuable tip to study Anki plugins in order to understand the inner workings of Anki, which led to this hack of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;stats.py&lt;/tt&gt; file, and also for general discussions about Anki to enhance the personal learning&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="languages"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning Italian for 30 days</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/learning-italian-for-30-days.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-09-17T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-17T23:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2018-09-17:/blog/learning-italian-for-30-days.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Results of the experiment to learn Italian autodidactically for one&amp;nbsp;month.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="the-settings"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;settings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of the year, I have decided to meet a few good friends in Italy this September. Having had no prior experience with the Italian language except for hearing conversations of others, I decided to start to learn Italian autodidactically from scratch approximately one month prior to my trip to Italy. Simply as an experiment about what is feasible in such a short amount of&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-stategy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My&amp;nbsp;stategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I have had good experiences with Duolingo for freshing up some rusty language skills as well as starting a completely new language, I decided to use the Duolingo app on my phone during the time of the experiment. Since I was working full time professionally, I limited the time spent on Duolingo to 5 minutes per&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different from how I used Duolingo earlier, I decided to accompany the Duolingo activity with daily review activities on Anki. I constrained myself to 5 minutes of Duolingo time because I wanted to put extra emphasis on Anki: Whatever I learned through Duolingo, I planned to type in Anki to repeat the Duolingo content even further. I knew that the time spent on Anki grows roughly linearly with time in the beginning of using Anki for a new subject so that utilising only 5 minutes per day for Duolingo plus the time spent on Anki to repeat the Duolingo content seemed realistic to me. I configured Anki to introduce 3 new cards to me per&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to focus on Anki because I&amp;#8217;ve had phenomenal experiences with Anki regarding other subjects. I use it daily for reviewing flash cards that deal with Physics, computer science and language knowledge. My experiences show that whatever I type into Anki burns into my mind, justifying spending more time on Anki than on Duolingo for this&amp;nbsp;experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-leading-questions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The leading&amp;nbsp;questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose for conducting this experiment is manyfold. The following questions were of interest to me, in increasing generalising&amp;nbsp;order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much of Italian is it possible to learn in one&amp;nbsp;month?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well do Duolingo and Anki play together? What are the timescales one is making progress for each of&amp;nbsp;them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well does the strategy work out for a language? I conjecture that the answer to that question generalises to other languages as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How realistic is such a strategy during working full&amp;nbsp;time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-results"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I conducted the experiment successfully without any days left out. Below, the Duolingo activity overview after half of the experiment can be&amp;nbsp;seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/learning_Italian_for_30_days/duolingo_scores.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/learning_Italian_for_30_days/duolingo_scores.png" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The Duolingo activity overview taken from the weekly emails one gets when using&amp;nbsp;Duolingo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following figure - taken from the Anki statistics feature - shows my Anki statistics after the whole experiment and reveals how many new words I learned, how much time I spent and how many flash cards I have reviewed, amongst&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/learning_Italian_for_30_days/statistics_composite.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/learning_Italian_for_30_days/statistics_composite.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;My Anki statistics of learning Italian for one month. Each letter corresponds to one evaluation and the letters (i) and (ii)
correspond to the monthly and yearly statistics, respectively. The latter is shown since I learned Italian for a few days more than one&amp;nbsp;month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most apparent results are the following ones. I&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8230; spent &lt;strong&gt;1 hour&lt;/strong&gt; of reviewing Anki flashcards with an average of &lt;strong&gt;1.4 minutes per day&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8230; reviewed &lt;strong&gt;708 flashcards&lt;/strong&gt; with an average of &lt;strong&gt;14.4 flashcards per day&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8230; spent an average of &lt;strong&gt;5.9s per cards&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8230; added &lt;strong&gt;162 flashcards&lt;/strong&gt; altogether. After the whole month, &lt;strong&gt;26 flashcards remained unseen&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter aspect reveals that Anki operates on a slower timescale than Duolingo does since I used solely Duolingo content for my Anki studies. Thus, when using Duolingo as an input for new content, the additional learning process with Anki is delayed. However, whatever is entered into Anki really burns into my mind. For me, it felt that if I progressed with Duolingo as fast as possible, the progress speed with the content from Duolingo would be slightly too fast for me. With that knowledge, I can adjust any future experiments with that fact in&amp;nbsp;mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting fact was that my very small experience of hearing Italian conversations really helped in studying Italian. It seemed to me like I knew the basic phonetics and potential ways to pronouce the words that I learned. This finding emphasises the advice that many experienced language learners give: Expose yourself to the spoken language as much as possible while learning the respective&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the same lines, learning a language in conjuntion with visiting the corresponding country once in a while makes sense. Not only does it boost one&amp;#8217;s motivation but it also familarises with the sound of the language. Last but not least, the native speakers you meet make up a large portion of the fun of learning a new&amp;nbsp;language!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="future-directions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Future&amp;nbsp;directions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most apparent extension to this experiment is to do it for a longer time, e.g. for one summer or one year. Since I would like to refresh another language first and want to try to use Anki for other types of knowledge at this point in time, I am not able to continue this experiment with Italian for now. However, I will use it with the afore mentioned other&amp;nbsp;language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me present to you what my conclusions&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One does learn quite a bit in such a short amount of time, even with limited time spent. However, since I was able to check my progress right in Italy, I have to admit that there is a lot more to be learned before a language is usable after an experiment like this. Anyway, it gave some good intro to that language and I&amp;#8217;d do it again for either the same or other&amp;nbsp;languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The experiment showed to me that Anki alone is not the best. By that, my experiment confirmed &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/docs/manual.html#downloading-shared-decks"&gt;Anki&amp;#8217;s recommendation&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to use Anki for stand-alone knowledge but to use it in conjuntion with other types of classes or&amp;nbsp;tutorials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the former, it is clear that also applying the gained knowledge is advisable. For instance with an additional language course, a tandem buddy, by writing texts or&amp;nbsp;traveling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No writing about Italy without a pretty&amp;nbsp;picture!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/learning_Italian_for_30_days/Napels_beach.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/learning_Italian_for_30_days/Napels_beach.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The cozy beach of Napels with the volcano &lt;em&gt;Mount Vesuvius&lt;/em&gt; in the&amp;nbsp;background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="languages"></category></entry></feed>