<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog - prototyping</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/feeds/prototyping.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://lellep.xyz/blog/</id><updated>2024-01-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Custom Case for your Digital Stylus</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/custom-stylus-case.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-01-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2024-01-12:/blog/custom-stylus-case.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Design of a custom case for your digital stylus. I use it every day and created it with&amp;nbsp;FreeCAD.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Note: If you&amp;#8217;re interested in downloading the customisable &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEP&lt;/span&gt; file, then scroll down to the solution&amp;nbsp;section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="contents topic" id="table-of-contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title first"&gt;Table of&amp;nbsp;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#the-problem" id="id1"&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#the-solution" id="id2"&gt;The&amp;nbsp;solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#conclusions" id="id3"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#acknowledgements" id="id4"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More&amp;nbsp;coverage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/D32tVKkaJzs"&gt;Link to YouTube Shorts video&lt;/a&gt; that introduces the&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-problem"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;The&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like using my digital stylus to write on my laptop for taking digital&amp;nbsp;notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle, my laptop has quite a neat magnetic mechanism to hold the stylus. Unfortunately, this mechanism fails when storing my laptop in my&amp;nbsp;backpack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-solution"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;The&amp;nbsp;solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of relying on the magnetic mechanism of my laptop, I will store the stylus in a custom case that I put in my backpack&amp;nbsp;separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that purpose, I designed a 3D printed case with an integrated thread, an attachment hole and stylus stand using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.freecad.org/"&gt;FreeCAD&lt;/a&gt;. This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.blender.org/"&gt;Blender&lt;/a&gt; render of the 3D&amp;nbsp;model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/custom_stylus_case/model_render.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/custom_stylus_case/model_render.jpg" style="width: 100%;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Render of the 3D model. Left panel shows the main body and right panel shows the top cap. The colours are merely for visual&amp;nbsp;guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the final&amp;nbsp;product:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/custom_stylus_case/model_printed.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/custom_stylus_case/model_printed.jpg" style="width: 60%;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Picture of the final product. Left panel shows the main body and right panel shows the top cap that also features a stylus stand. I printed the model in green &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case is super sturdy and the integrated 3D printed thread is very practical! The printed model has served me well so far and I use it every&amp;nbsp;day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attention&lt;/strong&gt;: Download the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; file shown in the first figure in form of a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STEP&lt;/span&gt; file &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/cad_file.step"&gt;by clicking here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used this case daily for the last few months, so that I am happy to confirm that 3D printing has proven itself to be very useful for a niche problem yet another&amp;nbsp;time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example of such a solution for a niche problem is my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3d-printed-bike-lock-mount.html"&gt;3D printed bike lock mount&lt;/a&gt; 🚲, where I mounted a lock to my bike using 3D&amp;nbsp;printing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="acknowledgements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks a lot to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.ucreatestudio.is.ed.ac.uk/"&gt;University of Edinburgh&amp;#8217;s uCreateStudio&lt;/a&gt; for letting me use their&amp;nbsp;printers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="3d printing"></category><category term="FreeCAD"></category></entry><entry><title>My small hobby laser cutter</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/my-small-hobby-laser-cutter.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2020-08-31:/blog/my-small-hobby-laser-cutter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I show my small K40-based hobby laser cutter setup. I include one bonus tip: How to make money with a laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div style="margin: 0px auto; text-align: center; border: 4px solid #d93200; border-radius: 10px; padding: 10px; width: 100%;"&gt;
    Did you come here for learning how to make money with a laser cutter? Then scroll down to the bonus tip of this article!
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this article, I am showing off my small 40W &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt;-ish Chinese laser cutter. I do so primarily to give back to the open source maker community, from which I learned a lot. Thank you at this point! As hobbyist makers are constantly gauging in which technology to get in next, I provide my experiences with setting up a small hobby laser cutter based on the infamous &amp;#8220;eBay laser cutter K40&amp;#8221; so that you can decide if laser cutting is a topic for you. It certainly was for&amp;nbsp;me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_cutting"&gt;laser cutting&lt;/a&gt; the first time back in 2017. There, I was able to use a 40W &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CO2&lt;/span&gt; laser cutter at the amazing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://edinburghhacklab.com/"&gt;Edinburgh Hacklab&lt;/a&gt; during their &amp;#8220;open night&amp;#8221;. The Hacklab not only provided the machine to use but also great services such as support on how to operate it, best practices and the material to use. They trusted even non-members enough to let you use it without constant surveillance, which I enjoyed very much. Furthermore, kudos to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fablab-karlsruhe.de/"&gt;Fablab Karlsruhe&lt;/a&gt; that gave me the best spontaneous workshop tour I ever experienced in a makerspace back in summer 2018. They explained me all the details of their huge and impressive &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article will be quite comprehensive and it will mostly deal with the technical aspects of my laser cutter, both in pictures and text. Furthermore, there is one bonus tip at the end, followed by my conclusion. Since I know that people are interested in how to make money with a laser cutter, I give a few tips and write down my experiences about it in the bonus&amp;nbsp;tip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post is not intended to be a general introduction to laser cutting. There are many aspects to laser cutting, such as how the machine itself works, how to focus it, which materials it can cut, how to create designs for it and so forth. Nevertheless, let me attempt to explain what a laser cutter is with a few sentences: A laser cutter is a machine that guides a powerful laser beam to a work piece in order to cut or engrave it. The work piece is typically a flat piece such as wood, acrylic or any other surface that is to be worked on. Sometimes also curved objects are processed. While there do exist diode-based laser cutters, the laser cutter I am talking about here uses a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CO2&lt;/span&gt; laser tube to generate the laser beam. This type of laser cutter is referred to as &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CO2&lt;/span&gt; laser cutter&lt;/em&gt; and they come at power levels of 40W or more. The laser beam is created in a stationary laser tube and then guided onto the work piece with reflective mirrors that can deal with such high powers. Lastly, the laser beam vaporises the material and thereby creates the cuts. There are big differences between the power levels of laser cutters and I am only talking about the lower end of the spectrum. Hence, after having explained to people that I own a small &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt;-ish laser cutter that can cut wood, leather and some plastics with its 40W, I typically had to negate their immediate question if I could cut some metal pieces for them. For metals, you need around &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://all3dp.com/2/laser-cutting-metal-how-to-get-started/"&gt;10x as much power&lt;/a&gt;. Larger machines might even have up to 100x as much power as my machine, meaning they offer a few kilo watts of laser output&amp;nbsp;power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having been attached to 3D printing for around 3 years at the time of 2017 when I was introduced to laser cutting, I was used to production cycles of multiple hours to finish a single 3D printed part. I always found that this is quite a long time for the impatient hobby-ist. Suddenly, there was a method to produce parts from flat surfaces in only minutes. I was amazed and knew that I needed access to such a machine in the future as to get deeper into rapid prototyping and small batch manufacturing with it. Since in Marburg there was no such machine anywhere close, I decided to build my own laser cutter at the end of&amp;nbsp;2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I based my small hobby laser off a Chinese laser cutter, commonly referred to as &lt;em&gt;K40 laser cutter&lt;/em&gt;. Finally, my laser cutter setup is shown in Fig. 1 with my laser cutter itself and some of the additional major modifications. The modifications will be explained later in this article with texts and pictures. This part makes up most of the article. The table of contents is given at the end of this section to make it easier for you to&amp;nbsp;navigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/overview_explained.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/overview_explained.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 1: My laser cutter setup. Some of my modifications are annotated with text. These modifications are explained later in this&amp;nbsp;article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="contents topic" id="table-of-contents"&gt;
&lt;p class="topic-title first"&gt;Table of&amp;nbsp;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#the-stock-k40-laser-cutter" id="id1"&gt;The stock K40 laser&amp;nbsp;cutter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#my-modifications-to-my-k40-laser-cutter" id="id2"&gt;My modifications to my K40 laser cutter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#laser-bed" id="id3"&gt;Laser&amp;nbsp;bed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#drag-chain" id="id4"&gt;Drag&amp;nbsp;chain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#air-assist" id="id5"&gt;Air&amp;nbsp;assist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#mirror-head" id="id6"&gt;Mirror&amp;nbsp;head&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#first-mirror-mount" id="id7"&gt;First mirror&amp;nbsp;mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#adjustable-laser-tube-mounts" id="id8"&gt;Adjustable laser tube&amp;nbsp;mounts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#leds" id="id9"&gt;LEDs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#control-panel" id="id10"&gt;Control&amp;nbsp;panel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#electronics-panel" id="id11"&gt;Electronics&amp;nbsp;panel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#water-cooling" id="id12"&gt;Water&amp;nbsp;cooling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#air-exhaust-system" id="id13"&gt;Air exhaust&amp;nbsp;system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#monitor-mount" id="id14"&gt;Monitor&amp;nbsp;mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#rolling-cart" id="id15"&gt;Rolling&amp;nbsp;cart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#self-made-tools" id="id16"&gt;Self made&amp;nbsp;tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#wood-pressing-machines" id="id17"&gt;Wood pressing&amp;nbsp;machines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#software" id="id18"&gt;Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#bonus-tip-making-money-with-a-laser-cutter" id="id19"&gt;Bonus tip: Making money with a laser&amp;nbsp;cutter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#conclusions" id="id20"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-stock-k40-laser-cutter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;The stock K40 laser&amp;nbsp;cutter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The K40 laser cutter is a small hobby grade &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CO2&lt;/span&gt; laser cutter made in China. At a price point of about $300 to $400, it comes with everything that is needed. This price is very cheap as comparable products such as the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.mr-beam.org/produkt/"&gt;Mr. Beam &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://glowforge.com/our-products"&gt;Glowforge series&lt;/a&gt; start at around $3000! Hence, it has been widely adapted in the maker community and there are many add-ons, hacks and reviews about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://donsthings.blogspot.com/"&gt;it&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/lasercutting"&gt;out&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChineseLaserCutters/"&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, it is a fully functional 40W &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CO2&lt;/span&gt; laser cutter with lots of accessories like pumps, extraction fans and software. However, since there is also no free lunch in the realm of power tools, the low price point comes at a cost. First and foremost, don&amp;#8217;t expect that the laser cutter works properly or at all upon arrival. All kinds of difficulties have been reported, such as misaligned laser beams, broken laser tubes or dirt spread all over the machine. Also, there are more disadvantages of the&amp;nbsp;machine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The control board is rather&amp;nbsp;limited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The K40 was initially made to etch rubber stamps and therefore comes with a very clumsy metal bracket to hold the material in place. It does not allow for adjustment in the height direction and limits the work area&amp;nbsp;heavily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 40W laser tube only reaches around 32W power output on&amp;nbsp;average.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The software is&amp;nbsp;bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The extraction fan is&amp;nbsp;bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The machine does not have an interlock system. Hence, it does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; disable the laser beam when you open the&amp;nbsp;lid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The frame of the machine is not grounded. Your life is seriously in danger at this point because the machine uses mains voltage and a high voltage line of 20kV to generate the laser&amp;nbsp;beam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought my laser off eBay from a local reseller located in Germany. This helps to avoid any difficulties with import regulations compared to buying directly from China. Interesting enough, I did not even pay more than what I would have paid when ordered from China directly. Figure 2 shows a representative offer of the K40 laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/ebay_listing.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/ebay_listing.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 2: Screenshot of a typical eBay listing of the K40 laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="my-modifications-to-my-k40-laser-cutter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;My modifications to my K40 laser&amp;nbsp;cutter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese laser cutters at this price point need to be seen as a base to start from. You can build a very well working laser cutter system by investing some (little) money and (more than little) time into&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have done a large number of modifications to my stock K40 laser cutter. I will go over all of these modifications in the following and explain&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="laser-bed"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Laser&amp;nbsp;bed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I replaced the mechanism to mount work pieces with a custom made laser bed from aluminium profiles. It features replaceable inlays that fit A4-sized wooden sheets and allows for around 4cm of z travel up and down. This travel is necessary to properly focus the laser beam onto the work piece. The z travel is realised by threaded rods. The bed is assembled with 3D printed parts. The knobs to adjust the z height are laser cut. The laser bed is mounted to the laser cutter frame with metal&amp;nbsp;screws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/laser_bed.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/laser_bed.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 3: Custom laser bed. (a) Laser bed with inlay inserted. (b) Laser bed without inlay to see the frame structure that is mounted to the machine frame. (c) Close-up of the inlay. The dirt comes from many hours of operation. (d) Connector piece for inlay assembly. (e) Mechanism to adjust the z&amp;nbsp;height.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="drag-chain"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Drag&amp;nbsp;chain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought a drag chain to reduce the chance of burning freely dangling cables inside the laser cutter. It is installed with a small 3D printed mount for the laser head and one from wood for the&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/drag_chain.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/drag_chain.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 4: The drag chain as indicated by the arrow. Electrical wires can be guided through it to reach the laser head. The drag chain is mounted to the frame of the machine and to the custom laser&amp;nbsp;head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="air-assist"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Air&amp;nbsp;assist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An air assist is a mechanism that pushes air onto the spot where the laser beam hits the work piece. It kills flames, adds oxygen to the cutting operation and typically also guides the fumes to be extracted out of the laser cutter. Normally, an air assist is realised by a compressor and a tube that guides the air to the work piece. Instead, I use a radial fan mounted to the laser head to serve the same purpose. This solution is powerful enough and comes with the benefit of being very silent. The mounting for the radial fan is 3D printed and guides the air right onto the spot where the laser hits the work piece. The electrical wire to drive the fan is routed to through the drag&amp;nbsp;chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/air_assist.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/air_assist.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 5: Air assist. (a) Radial fan mounted to the laser head to serve as air assist. The attached tape makes the assembly air-tight. (b) View from below to show the nozzle where the air is released onto the work&amp;nbsp;piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mirror-head"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Mirror&amp;nbsp;head&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of aligning the laser beam with the mirrors, I had to realise that the fixed-angle laser head that comes with the laser cutter is not sufficient for my purposes. This was because the linear motion system was not mounted properly into the frame, I believe. Luckily, the solution was easy: I needed a fully adjustable mirror in the laser head. For that, I turned towards &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; to model a fully featured laser head. The result is a laser head from 3D printed pieces, springs and metal screws. The assembly turned out to work beautifully and I used it ever&amp;nbsp;since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/mirror_head.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/mirror_head.lr.png" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 6: Fully adjustable laser head. (a) Overview of the laser head that includes the adjustable mirror, the air assist mounting and the drag chain mounting. (b) Close-up of the adjustable mirror. It follows the general rule of pre-tensioning the mirror mount with springs and three screws to fine tune the position against the pre-tensioning. (c) Top view of the mirror head. The three tensioning springs and three adjustment screws can be&amp;nbsp;seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="first-mirror-mount"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;First mirror&amp;nbsp;mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the alignment process of the laser beam it turned out that the maximal travel distance of the first mirror was not sufficiently large to properly align the laser beam. Hence, I replaced it with a fully adjustable mirror mount platform to allow for proper beam&amp;nbsp;alignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/first_mirror_mount.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/first_mirror_mount.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 7: Fully adjustable mirror platform indicated by the arrow. It is a piece of steel that is cut to size and has holes for the mirror mount as well as the adjustment knobs. The adjustment is achieved by two nuts that are screwed against the steel plate, one from the top and one from the bottom, in order to set the height of the plate. The lower nut is turned by a 3D printed knob that is shown in white. There are three of these height adjustment mechanisms. Also, the mirror bracket can be shifted backwards and forwards. After these rough adjustments, the mirror can be fine tuned with the adjustment knobs of the mirror mount itself. The path of the laser beam is shown by a dashed red line and points into the work area of the laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="adjustable-laser-tube-mounts"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Adjustable laser tube&amp;nbsp;mounts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the alignment process it turned out that the fixed laser tube mounts in the back of the machine where problematic as I couldn&amp;#8217;t adjust the position of the laser tube. Hence, I built my own fully adjustable laser tube mounts from 3D prints, metal screws and aluminium&amp;nbsp;profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/laser_tube_mounts.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/laser_tube_mounts.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 8: Fully adjustable laser tube mount. A C bracket from aluminium profiles is the main structure of the mount. It is installed into the laser cutter with metal screws. A 3D printed plastic piece attaches to the laser tube using zip ties and mounts to the C bracket. Two slots in the C bracket together with screws as linear motion system provide the possibility to adjust the position of the tube. The positions are adjusted with 3D printed knobs. The inset shows how the laser tube is mounted inside the laser cutter using two of my fully adjustable laser tube&amp;nbsp;mounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="leds"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;LEDs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is essential to see what the laser cutter does while in operation. Opening the lid while the laser is in operation is a bad idea because the machine does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; come with an interlock system and happily continues its job when you open the lid. Since the lid of the laser cutter has an built-in window, adding LEDs was the best approach to make the inner operations&amp;nbsp;visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/LEDs.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/LEDs.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 9: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; strip glued inside the machine to the front. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; strip is connected with a detachable connector. The inset shows this connection in greater&amp;nbsp;detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="control-panel"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Control&amp;nbsp;panel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left the control panel of the laser cutter mostly untouched. Make sure to get the K40 version with the analogue ampere meter as it is more reliable than the digital versions that come with some of the K40 variations. An accurate current measurement is crucial because if the current is too high, the laser tube is damaged and you need to replace it. This can be quite a pain as the tube is one of the most expensive components of a laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/control_panel.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/control_panel.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 10: The control panel of the laser cutter. From top to bottom, the arrows indicate the analogue ampere meter, the current dial and the laser test switch. I attached a gauge to the current dial to get the power levels right and had to replace the laser test switch as the original&amp;nbsp;broke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="electronics-panel"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Electronics&amp;nbsp;panel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I introduced an electronics panel to add a few convenience features to the laser cutter and its operation. These features include &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; lights to illuminate the work area as well as an air assist. The electronics panel allows to switch all of these features&amp;nbsp;easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/electronics_panel.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/electronics_panel.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 11: Electronics panel. (a) Front view. The third switch is currently not used and provides room for future upgrades. (b) The inner wiring of the electronics panel. It distributes 12V to the&amp;nbsp;switches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="water-cooling"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Water&amp;nbsp;cooling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the laser tube produces around 30 to 40W of output power, it produces around 10x as much heat in that process. If the laser tube is not cooled, it gets too warm and is destroyed. Hence, water cooling is necessary. The machine came with a small aquarium pump which worked flawlessly in my case. I added a bucket of distilled water with a chemical to reduce algae growth in a low concentration. Also, I added a thermometer to monitor the water temperature. The bucket has a custom lid with holes for the water tubes that reach to the laser. Also, the lid enables me to easily insert a bottle with frozen water in it in case the cooling water gets too warm. This is typically the case in summer. Using this strategy, I am able to operate the machine below a cooling water temperature of 20 degree&amp;nbsp;Celsius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/water_cooling.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/water_cooling.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 12: Water cooling. (a) Water cooling solution as realised by a bucket of distilled water. (b) Close-up of the setup to show how the custom lid allows the insertion of a bottle of frozen water, the thermometer and the water tubes to the laser cutter. The wooden piece that is attached to the plastic lid provides extra stability for the custom&amp;nbsp;lid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="air-exhaust-system"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Air exhaust&amp;nbsp;system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laser cutter evaporates material to perform the cutting. The fumes that stem from this process, while not being toxic when using the correct materials, smell very bad and need to be extracted from within the laser cutter out into the free. The air exhaust fan that comes with the laser cutter and its mechanism to mount it to the machine are pretty bad and should be replaced. I did so by building a custom air exhaust fan from an old 300W motor I had laying around. The power is reduced to around 200W with a power resistor that is mounted inside the wooden fan box to get sufficient cooling for the resistor. The 200W system is absolutely sufficient and still much stronger than the 25W stock air exhaust fan. Also, I made a custom attachment for the air extraction hose to the back of the machine from wood. The laser cutter is placed close to a window so that the extracted air is blown out of the&amp;nbsp;workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/air_exhaust_system.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/air_exhaust_system.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 13: Air exhaust system. The two insets from left to right show the custom air exhaust fan and the custom attachment for the air extraction hose to the laser, respectively. The blue hose came with the machine and is quite stiff. I bought the white one to connect the fan to the attachment on the laser cutter. The air exhaust fan features a custom laser cut control box that is visible in the left of the left inset. The fan is sealed with black tape. The hose connection pieces for both, the fan and the box, are 3D printed pieces but they are not visible&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="monitor-mount"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Monitor&amp;nbsp;mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A laser cutter is typically controlled from a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;. After around 2 weeks I had enough of flimsy laptop setups next to the machine and installed a workshop &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; with a proper monitor mount. The mount allows for easy rotations with two degrees of freedom. It is a super simple design made from wood but very sturdy and incredibly useful in the daily operation of the machine. The monitor mount is attached to a shelf that is located next to the laser cutter. The attached monitor connects to the workshop &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;. This modification is one of the most useful&amp;nbsp;ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/monitor_mount.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/monitor_mount.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 14: Unfolded monitor mount, showing the wooden construction. The monitor is mounted with its &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VESA&lt;/span&gt; connections and can be folded in when not in operation, see the inset. The blue arrow marks the WiFi &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USB&lt;/span&gt; adapter of the workshop &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; to connect it to the&amp;nbsp;internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="rolling-cart"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Rolling&amp;nbsp;cart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laser cutter stands on a rolling cart. This rolling cart used to be a simple shelf that I put on wheels with a strong metal frame. Also, I added a solid top work plate to it to place the laser cutter on. The rolls allow me to move the machine easily. The drawers store all the tools and accessories that I need to operate the laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/rolling_cart.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/rolling_cart.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 15: The rolling cart. (a) Overview with all drawers closed. (b) to (e) show each of the drawers with the different accessories I use. Most frequently, I use the keyboard and mouse in the top drawer shown in (b) to operate the workshop &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;. The drawer shown in (c) holds all the tools. The drawers (d) and (e) accommodate some of the wood that I laser cut as well as past&amp;nbsp;projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="self-made-tools"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Self made&amp;nbsp;tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the installation and calibration process of the laser cutter, I made a few tools that made my life easier. The more interesting ones are shown in Fig.&amp;nbsp;16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/self_made_tools.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/self_made_tools.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 16: Self made tools. (a) Laser beam alignment helper. In order to align the laser beam, one needs to check if it hits the centers of the mirrors. In order to judge if it does, I developed a small 3D printed magnetic stand that accepts pieces of paper and that can be mounted right in front of the mirrors. The laser beam burns the piece of paper that is installed in the alignment helper so that one can see where the infrared (and therefore invisible) laser beam hit the mirror. Once the piece of paper is burned too much, it can be replaced easily. (b) Laser beam alignment helper for vertical direction when the laser beam hits the work piece. With this tool, I can ensure that the laser beam hits the work piece in a 90 degree angle. Again, a piece of paper can be attached to it. To properly align the vertical beam direction, the piece of paper can be moved up and down guided by the two short screws. (c) Laser tube rack. When doing work on the laser tube, I hook these holders in the back of the laser cutter and place the tube onto them temporarily. With that, I don&amp;#8217;t need to disconnect the tube from its electrical wires and the water cooling tubes. (d) Nut screwing helper. When working with metal screws in hard-to-reach places, I can place the nut at the end of this helper. It holds the nut in place, avoids any spinning of the nut and is thinner than my fingers so that I can reach places I could not&amp;nbsp;otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wood-pressing-machines"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Wood pressing&amp;nbsp;machines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite plywood tends to warp. Hence, I place the wood, that is to be used with the laser cutter, in a machine that makes sure the wood does not warp over&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/wood_pressing_machines.hr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/wood_pressing_machines.lr.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 17: Versions 1 and 2 of the wood pressing machine. (a) The first version used threaded rods to fix the wood between two thick wooden pieces. As it was quite cumbersome to use this version, it has been retired and replaced by a second version. (b) The second version is just a piece of wood and a very heavy anvil that compresses the pile of wooden pieces beneath it. It works&amp;nbsp;great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="software"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stock software that comes with the laser cutter neither worked well nor did it run on Linux. However, there is a beautiful open source implementation of a control software: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.scorchworks.com/K40whisperer/k40whisperer.html"&gt;K40 whisperer&lt;/a&gt;, which works well and runs on&amp;nbsp;Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/k40_whisperer.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/my_small_hobby_laser_cutter/k40_whisperer.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 18: Screenshot of K40 whisperer. Picture taken from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.scorchworks.com/K40whisperer/k40whisperer.html"&gt;the K40 whisperer website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bonus-tip-making-money-with-a-laser-cutter"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Bonus tip: Making money with a laser&amp;nbsp;cutter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this bonus tip, I would like to write down some notes on how to make money with a laser cutter. Based on my experiences, making money with a laser cutter is possible. In particular on a small hobby-ist laser cutter as such a machine is very affordable. This makes it easy to begin your, for example, side&amp;nbsp;business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me state my thoughts on that topic in the following unsorted&amp;nbsp;list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get in contact with local entrepreneurs. Maybe they have a regular meeting that you could attend. Typically, these communities are often very interested and very supportive. In Marburg, there is for example &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://de-de.facebook.com/gruendervirus/"&gt;GruenderVirus&lt;/a&gt;. At the very least, attending events of these communities is business networking. This is a very valuable&amp;nbsp;activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for business or idea competitions to participate in. They might be a good place to get some attention. Generally, make sure that people know what you do. You want to be known as &amp;#8220;that laser cutter&amp;nbsp;guy&amp;#8221;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be generous with give-aways. Small give-aways literally cost you nothing but are a great way to promote your laser cutter&amp;nbsp;business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar to the previous point: Have prototypes and small things ready to show off! You, as a tech affine maker, might not believe it but people sometimes cannot understand the broad spectrum of objects a laser cutter can produce. Having small demonstration items ready helps a lot for your future customers to understand what kind of things you can fabricate. Aside from different designs, I also recommend different materials and different finishes. Take, for example, wood stain, which can change the look of regular wood&amp;nbsp;completely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of presentation channels. Maybe a website? Maybe some kind of social media like Instagram? Once you established a channel, prepare loads of content for it to keep your audience busy. Oh, and don&amp;#8217;t forget to track your audience for analysing the performance of your channels. The channel that I used was a minimalist website: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/laser"&gt;http://lellep.xyz/laser&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value your work time. Do not work for free but always take into account the time you will spend on a project in your pricing. Especially when you begin it is very tempting to remove your personal cost from the equation in order to decrease your price. Please take my words of warning: Not valuing your own working time might back fire at some&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not work with everybody. If you don&amp;#8217;t like your potential business partner - say, a person who wants to order something from you - then just don&amp;#8217;t work with that person. Getting a job done for somebody involves a quite tight relationship for a short amount of time and if you see potential problems arising due to differences in personalities, then just don&amp;#8217;t do it. Assuming you pursue your ambition of making money with a laser cutter seriously, please take my word when I say that other, much more pleasant, business relation will come for&amp;nbsp;sure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get a business license. Only with that, you are on the safe side regarding taxes. Also, it enables you to offer your service more professionally. Not being registered means that you cannot scale your business beyond a certain&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a goal. For instance, a good goal might be to earn the money back that you invested into the laser cutter machine itself. Given my very positive experience with Chinese laser cutters, I would always argue to get a decent Chinese machine. With that, the initial investment should be around $300 to $4000, which is an ideal intermediate financial goal to reach. After passing this number, you could deliberately stop your ambitions if you find that you don&amp;#8217;t like laser cutting as a business as much as you&amp;nbsp;thought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potentially: Find a niche. Start-up people always say that you have to find a niche: For example, the first people to write a blog on travel adventures made a fortune with it. I am not totally convinced of that statement when it comes to laser cutting. That is because a laser cutter is a very versatile machine that can deliver a multitude of products. Anyways,&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8230; invest at least a little bit of thought upfront in the objects that you want to sell. Is it ear rings, merchandise, is it &lt;span class="caps"&gt;B2B&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;B2C&lt;/span&gt;? None of these decisions need to be final but you will see that there is just not enough time to serve all possible business directions. Having a rough plan, or better a rough analysis of the market opportunities, helps a lot in staying focused later&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish a workflow to reduce the time you need for finishing a job. Think of how to organise your laser cutter design files, how to organise your business contacts and set up your laser cutter in a way that makes it easy to work with. For example, I found that a well designed Excel spreadsheet is useful for documenting my work and coming up with a price. Also, I used a cloud service to transfer the design data to my workshop &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; as to reduce the time it takes to finish a project. Lastly, getting the right tools is necessary for an optimised workflow. For example, for assembling laser cut objects, I found the following tools to be useful: Rubber bands, masking tape, (wood) glue, precision tools (to remove excess glue, for example), clamps and something heavy to compress wet&amp;nbsp;glue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build your machine thoroughly. Once you get laser cutter jobs, you do not want to disappoint your customers because your laser cutter broke after just a few hours of work time. Rather invest a few more hours to build the machine properly. You will benefit from it in the long&amp;nbsp;run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a Chinese laser cutter for commercial interests is a great way to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/bootstrap.asp"&gt;bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; a business, I believe. So go out and do&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusions"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#table-of-contents"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot working on this project! First, I learned technical aspects on how a laser cutter works, how to operate it and how to make designs for it. In particular, fixing the Chinese stock K40 laser cutter to become a fully functional machine was good fun! For example, I learned how to make complex &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; designs with it such as the adjustable mirror head, air assist and laser bed. Second, I learned many business aspects that might become useful at some&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, would I do it all again? Yes, I&amp;nbsp;would!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, now that I know how to fix and customise a Chinese laser cutter, I would probably get a larger machine. The price levels typically go as $400, $800, $1300, $2000. I would probably aim for a $2000 machine since I know that getting the money back through laser cutting jobs is realistic. The most interesting aspect of a more expensive laser cutter is the larger work area. The reason that this is so interesting is what people call &lt;em&gt;scaling&lt;/em&gt;: A larger machine can produce designs with less manual intervention. Hence, you can produce more in a given time, which makes you much more competitive in the&amp;nbsp;market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not have any commercial interest in laser cutting, I fully recommend the K40 laser cutter. If you do but you&amp;#8217;re not sure, yet, then still get the K40 machine as you can upgrade later if necessary. Only get a larger machine if you really know that you are seriously interested in getting in the business of laser&amp;nbsp;cutting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out to me if you have any more questions regarding laser cutting. I am happy to help makers with some advice to get their laser&amp;nbsp;cutter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Running list of designs</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/running-list-of-designs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2020-05-24:/blog/running-list-of-designs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A list of small designs like 3D prints, laser cuts and other constructions. Most of them serve a functional purpose. This list is continuously&amp;nbsp;updated.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here, I show a continuously updated list of small constructions. Most of them solve a specific problem so that the majority of the designs can be considered &lt;em&gt;functional designs&lt;/em&gt;.
Each section starts with the functional design&amp;#8217;s name as headline and documents the design with a short description, a date and&amp;nbsp;pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in any of construction files, e.g. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SVG&lt;/span&gt; or any other format, then please contact me. I am happy to look for the files and to send them to&amp;nbsp;you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here comes the list of all&amp;nbsp;objects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#bluetooth-speaker-box"&gt;Bluetooth speaker&amp;nbsp;box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#spray-paint-rack"&gt;Spray paint&amp;nbsp;rack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#key-hanging-board"&gt;Key hanging&amp;nbsp;board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#green-office-accent"&gt;Green office&amp;nbsp;accent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#diy-video-light"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; video&amp;nbsp;light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#wooden-phone-tripod-mount"&gt;Wooden phone tripod&amp;nbsp;mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#wooden-camera-rig"&gt;Wooden camera&amp;nbsp;rig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#photo-box"&gt;Photo&amp;nbsp;box&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#office-headphone-hook"&gt;Office headphone&amp;nbsp;hook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bluetooth-speaker-box"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bluetooth speaker&amp;nbsp;box&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;03/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: A wooden box to safely store my bluetooth speaker. The box is made from (cheap) wood, covered with wood filler and painted with brown colour. Fleece pads have been added to the inner compartment to ensure that the bluetooth speaker is not&amp;nbsp;damaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/bluetooth_speaker_box/overview.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/bluetooth_speaker_box/overview.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="spray-paint-rack"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spray paint&amp;nbsp;rack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;Q1/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: A small rack to store spray paint cans under a sink in my wood workshop. The rack is made from scrap wood that is older than&amp;nbsp;me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/spray_paint_rack/overview.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/spray_paint_rack/overview.jpg" style="width: 300px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="key-hanging-board"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key hanging&amp;nbsp;board&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;12/24/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: A custom-made board from recycled wood for hanging keys. The engraving and small ornaments have been fabricated on my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/my-small-hobby-laser-cutter.html"&gt;laser cutter&lt;/a&gt;. The board is used daily when leaving and entering the&amp;nbsp;appartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/key_hanging_board/overview.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/key_hanging_board/overview.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="green-office-accent"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Green office&amp;nbsp;accent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;Q4/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: Laser-cut box that has been treated with wood stain to place a bit of green onto my home office&amp;nbsp;desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/green_office_accent/overview.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/green_office_accent/overview.png" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="diy-video-light"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; video&amp;nbsp;light&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;05/23/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: A light constructed around 12V &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; strips and controlled with a simple switch. This light will help me to illuminate videos and photos better. It is driven by a 12V power source. To diffuse the set of discrete light sources of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; strip, a sanded piece of transparent acrylic is attached to the front. It turns out that the light quality is very decent and the brightness is very&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/diy_video_light/overview.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/diy_video_light/overview.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; video light. (a) Front picture of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt; video light. (b) Close-up of the switch and 12V plug&amp;nbsp;adapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Rf8XJOXHsWg"
            frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wooden-phone-tripod-mount"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wooden phone tripod&amp;nbsp;mount&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;05/23/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: A mount for attaching a smartphone to a tripod for photo and video purposes. The mount comes with a standard 1/4 inch photo screw and uses a spring loaded clamping mechanism to cover a wide range of phone widths. Fleece and small stop blocks ensure that the phone is not&amp;nbsp;damaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/wooden_phone_tripod_mount/summary.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/wooden_phone_tripod_mount/summary.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Wooden phone tripod mount. (a) Project overview. (b) Adjustment screw to set the desired phone mounting width. (c) The fleece pads and stop blocks to protect the phone from being damaged. Also, view on the spring loaded adjustment mechanism. (d) 1/4 inch photo thread in the top and functional part of the spring loaded adjustment mechanism in the&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/n7bs4HeCHFc"
            frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="wooden-camera-rig"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wooden camera&amp;nbsp;rig&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;05/20/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: Although the video quality of modern smartphones is very good, the resulting shots can be shaky. This wooden camera rig adds proper handles and weight to the phone in its role as video camera and thereby solves the issue of shaky phone videos. Of course, it can be used with any camera as it offers the standard 1/4 inch screw. I got information on these standard photography parts &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.fotoschraubenshop.de/info-1/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/wooden_camera_rig/summary.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/wooden_camera_rig/summary.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Wooden camera rig. (a) Project overview. The holes in the top can be used to mount extra video gear, such as video lights or microphones. (b) 3D printed assembly that uses the 1/4 inch screw from a cheap 1€ tripod with a screwing mechanism to ensure a tight bond between camera rig and video camera. (c) Holes in the bottom of the rig allow extra weight to be added as to make the shots even more smooth. (d) Fleece pads on the&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CTRx8avhNWU"
            frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="photo-box"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Photo&amp;nbsp;box&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;03/28/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: A place that can be used to take pictures with proper illumination. The box consists of 1cm diameter &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PVC&lt;/span&gt; pipes that are connected with 3D printed corner
pieces. The sides are covered by cardboard with baking paper insert that serves as&amp;nbsp;diffusor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/photo_box/1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/photo_box/1.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Finished photo box with installed &amp;#8220;infinity background&amp;#8221;, the three lamps and side panels that include the&amp;nbsp;diffusors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/photo_box/2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/photo_box/2.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Photo box without side panels in order to show the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PVC&lt;/span&gt; pipe frame. Surprisingly, it is quite&amp;nbsp;rigid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/photo_box/3.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/photo_box/3.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Close-up of the 3D printed corners that hold together the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PVC&lt;/span&gt; pipe edges. The corners are attached to the pipes with 3mm metal&amp;nbsp;screws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="office-headphone-hook"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Office headphone&amp;nbsp;hook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;:&amp;nbsp;2018/2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: This plastic hook, which screws into the office desk with an M6 screw, provides a place for me to hang my headphones at work. This helps to avoid damaging my headphones as they fell on the ground&amp;nbsp;previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/office_headphone_hook/overview.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/running_list_of_designs/office_headphone_hook/overview.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Office headphone hook. (a) Headphones hanged to the hook while I don&amp;#8217;t use the headphones. (b) Hook as I use the headphones so that they are not hanging&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Xournal++ Community Gift</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/xournalpp-community-gift.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2020-05-23:/blog/xournalpp-community-gift.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A laser cut community gift for Xournal++&amp;nbsp;developers.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I really like open-source software! Daily, I use amazing open-source software for all kinds of&amp;nbsp;tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two such applications are &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://xournal.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Xournal&lt;/a&gt; and its successor &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/xournalpp/xournalpp"&gt;Xournal++&lt;/a&gt;. I use it for taking handwritten notes on my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; for many of my professional and private projects. Already Xournal is amazing but Xournal++ adds on top of that many useful&amp;nbsp;features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017, when I was trying to install Xournal++ from its &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/xournalpp/xournalpp"&gt;git repository&lt;/a&gt;, there was little development going on for the Xournal++ project. Over the course of the last two to three years, Xournal++ regained popularity and the open-source community continued to develop Xournal++ very actively. I think that&amp;#8217;s a great community effort and I hope that this will&amp;nbsp;continue!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s make it short: I used Xournal++ to build a laser cutter. Hence, I figured out that giving back to the community by providing a small laser cut gift would be necessary. I designed two small designs that you can see in the figure&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/xournalpp_community_gift/designs.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/xournalpp_community_gift/designs.jpg" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I rendered a small 360 degree video to fully show what the small key chain looks like. I laser cut it from 3mm &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MDF&lt;/span&gt; and it is 8cm by 2cm in size so that it should fit on any key&amp;nbsp;easily:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eMyXtzM8uJg"
            frameborder="0"
            allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a gift to the community without any strings attached - except maybe that I would like the community to continue to develop the amazing software Xournal++&amp;nbsp;:-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laser cut gift is genuinely for free. However, I need to ship it. I live in Germany, so that I restrict my gift to Germany-only. My budget for the shipping costs is 10€. Assuming a &amp;#8220;standard letter&amp;#8221; as shipping method, which is 0.8€, the 10€ in budget translate into 13 key chain gifts that I will ship to Xournal++ developers in Germany. I won&amp;#8217;t include the key rings but anticipate that everybody has one&amp;nbsp;already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sorry for non-German Xournal++ developers. Here you can find the design: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/xournalpp_community_gift.05232020.svg"&gt;click&lt;/a&gt;. Using blue lines for vector engraving and red lines for vector cutting, you can fabricate your own key chains with this&amp;nbsp;design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, contact me here if you would like to receive one of the key chains: &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:martin.lellep.blog&amp;#64;gmail.com"&gt;martin.lellep.blog&amp;#64;gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for developing&amp;nbsp;Xournal++!&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>How to use 3D scanning for CAD modeling</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/how-to-use-3d-scanning-for-cad-modeling.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2020-05-10:/blog/how-to-use-3d-scanning-for-cad-modeling.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I show how to use 3D scanning for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling and how I built a custom &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse box with the method that I present here.
Neither do you need a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; nor a powerful &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; to follow along this tutorial. Also, the 3D scanning software is for&amp;nbsp;free.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;div style="margin: 0px auto; text-align: center; border: 4px solid #d93200; border-radius: 25px; padding: 20px; width: 80%;"&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Teaser&amp;nbsp;trailer&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aft_jvATzFQ"
            frameborder="0"
            allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="introduction"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer-aided_design"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling&lt;/a&gt; for building things is awesome! However, when it comes to organic shapes,
that cannot be made up of the typical squares and circles, even designers with an intermediate skill level start to&amp;nbsp;struggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, 3D scanning can help to get 3D models of organically shaped&amp;nbsp;objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, I show you here how to utilise 3D scanning specifially for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling - and all that without the need for a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; or a powerful &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;.
As an exemplary project that also solves one of my (not so important) problems, I set myself to design a box for my (organically shaped) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse.
This will help me to carry my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse in my backpack more&amp;nbsp;easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the agenda for this&amp;nbsp;tutorial:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#scan-preparations"&gt;Scan preparations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#d-scanning-with-meshroom"&gt;3D scanning with Meshroom&lt;/a&gt; - an open-source photogrammetry software - using the free &lt;em&gt;Google Cloud&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#d-model-post-processing"&gt;3D model post processing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#building-a-cad-model-around-the-3d-scan"&gt;Building a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; model around the 3D scan&lt;/a&gt; - using &lt;em&gt;Autodesk Fusion 360&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#fabrication-and-assembly-of-the-mouse-box"&gt;Fabrication and assembly of the mouse box&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#final-product"&gt;Final product&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference internal" href="#acknowledgments"&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="scan-preparations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scan&amp;nbsp;preparations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we use photogrammetry here, the texture of the object to be scanned should be as feature-rich and dull as possible.
If the object you plan to scan is shiny, you have to make sure to cover it in some non-shiny material: Some people use
painter&amp;#8217;s tape, special powder or simply flour if your object permits. Furthermore, as photogrammetry identifies features
of your object, or generally speaking your whole scene, you should also make sure that the whole scene in which you take
the photos is&amp;nbsp;feature-rich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, I am scanning my portable computer mouse here. Since it is shiny, I covered it in painter&amp;#8217;s tape that I
removed later on again. Additionally, I drew random symbols on that painter&amp;#8217;s tape to assist the photogrammetry software to find
distinct features that can be matched throughout the set of&amp;nbsp;pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G-UAAbKWsxk"
            frameborder="0"
            allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
    &lt;p class="caption"&gt;
        Video 1: All photos of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse rendered into one video. The individual picture quality has been
        reduced for this video in order to ensure a reasonably small video file size. The quality of
        the images used for the 3D scan, however, has not been reduced in any way as to get the highest scan&amp;nbsp;quality.
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The animation in Vid. 1 shows a video of all the images that I used for the photogrammetry procedure. As you can see in Vid. 1,
I made sure to cover the object in all possible angles, even multiple times and including close-ups of sections that might
need additional coverage. To ensure enough distinct features in the scene, I designed an A4 sheet printout with random symbols
on it: You can download it &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3D_scanning_print_out.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to print
the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the whole set of images I used a phone camera. I shot it outside on a cloudy day to guarantee an even lighting as photogrammetry
does not cope well with hard&amp;nbsp;shadows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="d-scanning-with-meshroom"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3D scanning with&amp;nbsp;Meshroom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use the free and amazing software &lt;em&gt;Meshroom&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://alicevision.org/"&gt;https://alicevision.org/&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/alicevision/meshroom"&gt;https://github.com/alicevision/meshroom&lt;/a&gt;) to perform the 3D
scan of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse, see Fig. 1 for a screenshot of Meshroom. There are great tutorials on Meshroom out there. I used, for example, this one:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k4NTf0hMjtY"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k4NTf0hMjtY&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/meshroom_2019.2.0.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/meshroom_2019.2.0.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 1: Meshroom version 2019.2.0 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; screenshot. The whole computation performed by Meshroom is defined by the &amp;#8220;Graph Editor&amp;#8221;
in the bottom and consumes pictures imported into the &amp;#8220;Images&amp;#8221; area. The final result is shown in the &amp;#8220;3D&amp;nbsp;Viewer&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Meshroom requires a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CUDA&lt;/span&gt;-capable (i.e. somewhat powerful) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; to yield the best 3D scanning results. In the following, I show
how to run Meshroom (a) without a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; on your computer at the cost of lower scan quality and (b) in the Google cloud on &lt;em&gt;Google Colab&lt;/em&gt; for free
at the cost of lacking a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt;. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; of Meshroom is well thought through and only executes underlying binary
command line tools that can also be invoked without the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt;. Most of what I am stating here is knowledge collected from the internet so that I can redirect you
to the original sources for in-depth explanations. In the following paragraphs, I expect you to have watched some tutorial on Meshroom as a
dedicated tutorial will explain the details of Meshroom much better than I could ever do&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run Meshroom on your computer without a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; you should check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/alicevision/meshroom/wiki/Draft-Meshing"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.
Also &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/alicevision/meshroom/wiki/Error:-This-program-needs-a-CUDA-Enabled-GPU"&gt;this resource&lt;/a&gt; is very good. In summary,
you remove some of the default steps from the Meshroom computation pipeline, the depth map computation to be specific, in order to remove the computation
steps that require a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;. Depending on your computer hardware, the computation might only take a few minutes with these settings. The scan of my mouse
with this technique is shown in Fig. 2&amp;nbsp;(b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we look into how to run Meshroom in the cloud on a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; - for free. The scan of my mouse with this technique is shown in Fig. 2 (a). The procedure is as follows: You start a Google Colab instance, add a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; runtime,
upload your images and start the Meshroom commandline binary after downloading it. Since Google Colab runs with Jupyter Notebooks, all these tasks can
be performed easily. Please check out the following notebook that I put together for you in order to start using Google Colab for 3D scanning right now:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3D_scanning_colab_notebook.ipynb"&gt;click&lt;/a&gt;. I based my
notebook off publicly available information, such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/alicevision/meshroom/wiki/Meshroom-in-Google-Colab-(cloud)"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. My notebook works as&amp;nbsp;follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pictures must be uploaded to the Colab instance as&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;my_dataset.zip&amp;#8221;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subsequently, they are automatically unzipped, processed and finally the 3D scan is zipped to be&amp;nbsp;downloaded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My notebook is quite straightforward and well documented. Therefore, check out my comments and texts in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3D_scanning_colab_notebook.ipynb"&gt;the Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3D scan is saved by Meshroom as an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OBJ&lt;/span&gt; file that includes both 3D mesh information as well as the texture of the object. Figure 2 shows the results
of the 3D scan for both of the approaches, with and without &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;,&amp;nbsp;respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/with_vs_without_GPU.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/with_vs_without_GPU.png" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 2: 3D scans of my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse using Meshroom. (a) Scan result using a cloud &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; to enable the full computation pipeline &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; highest quality of Meshroom.
(b) Scan result using Meshroom&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt;-only computation&amp;nbsp;steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt;-only computation pipeline is quicker to compute and executable on any computer, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;-enabled features of Meshroom do increase
the quality of the 3D scan significantly. They require a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; and take slightly longer to compute, on the order of one hour vs on the order of minutes. Figure 2
might not be able to convey the detailed differences between the models, as it is just an image, but the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;-enabled scan is much more detailed than the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt;-only scan: The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt;-only
model consists of 43,512 scanned faces while the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;-enabled scan consists of 1,043,705 scanned faces. Hence, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;-enabled scan detected almost 20x more
faces than the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt;-only model using the exact same pictures of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I recommend to always use a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; to compute Meshroom 3D scans, in particular taking Google Colab into account as it offers free &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; compute&amp;nbsp;power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="d-model-post-processing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3D model post&amp;nbsp;processing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As photogrammetry identifies features in the images that are used in order to derive the camera perspectives, the scans might pick up parts of the
scene in which the scan is created. I used a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3D_scanning_print_out.pdf"&gt;custom-made printout&lt;/a&gt;
to ensure that there are enough distinct features. Figure 3 (a) shows the raw
scan that comes out of Meshroom using the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;-enabled computation pipeline executed on Google Colab and Fig. 3 (b) shows the same scan but a manually tidied up version of it. I used &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.blender.org/"&gt;Blender&lt;/a&gt; to remove all excess parts of the scan that are not of&amp;nbsp;relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/raw_scan_vs_trimmed.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/raw_scan_vs_trimmed.png" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 3: Cleaned 3D scan. (a) The model as computed by Meshroom. (b) Manually trimmed model to only consist of the mouse itself and no more scene&amp;nbsp;parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, removing the artefacts is a mandatory step here. Depending on what you want to do with your scanned model, there is another mandatory step:
Reducing the complexity of the 3D model by removing vertices. The original model as shown in Fig. 3 (a) consists of 1,043,705 faces and the trimmed
model in Fig. 3 (b) consists of only 423,706 faces without reducing the model quality at all as only the excess parts of the scan were removed.
For many applications though, even these 400k faces are too many. One such application being (consumer-grade) CADs (on a consumer-grade &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt;), I removed
the number of faces even further before exporting the model to an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; file. Figure 4 shows exactly&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/stl_resolutions.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/stl_resolutions.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 4: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; models of my scanned &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse after reducing the number of faces. (a) The original file as shown in Fig. 3 (b) after exporting it
to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; (and, hence, without texture) with 423,706 faces. (b) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; with the number of faces reduced to 15% of the original model. (c) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; with the
number of faces reduced to 0.15% of the original model. Subfigures (b) and (c) were generated with Blender by using its
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.blender.org/manual/en/latest/modeling/modifiers/generate/decimate.html"&gt;decimate modifier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I wanted to use the model to design a box around it, I needed it in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt;. Most of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; software support generic model formats like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OBJ&lt;/span&gt;
but can also transform these formats to their native data format. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m5v8JO7pEAk"&gt;These&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://toglefritz.com/convert-a-simple-stl-into-a-body-in-fusion-360/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; resources show how to transform an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; to Fusion 360&amp;#8217;s native data format. This is very useful for all subsequent design steps but it comes at a high computational cost when the model is too detailed. Hence, I used the model shown in Fig. 4 (c) for being converted to a
native Fusion 360 object and to model my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse box&amp;nbsp;around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="building-a-cad-model-around-the-3d-scan"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; model around the 3D&amp;nbsp;scan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the coarse-grained &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; shown in Fig. 4 (c) to build my box around it. To do so, I imported it into Fusion 360 - the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; I am using here - and designed a wooden
box around it. In order to take advantage of having the organic shape of my mouse in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt;, I designed custom 3D printed pieces as inserts for the wooden box to
ensure that the mouse does not move around inside the box while carrying it&amp;nbsp;on-the-go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To have the full capabilities of Fusion at hand for my mouse 3D scan, I converted it into the native Fusion data format as mentioned in the previous section. With this, I was able to use my scan with all joints and features inside Fusion. My finished &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; model is shown in Vid.&amp;nbsp;2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/69HpqAb9VaY"
            frameborder="0"
            allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
    &lt;p class="caption"&gt;
        Video 2: Video of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; model of the mouse transportation box. The 3D scanned model of my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse is shown in black.
        White pieces are 3D printed plastic pieces from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt; and the wooden box is shown in wood-brown. The wooden box will
        be laser&amp;nbsp;cut.
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="fabrication-and-assembly-of-the-mouse-box"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fabrication and assembly of the mouse&amp;nbsp;box&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made use of my private 3D printer to fabricate the organically shaped custom inner blocks for the wooden box. The wooden box itself,
I fabricated on my small hobby laser&amp;nbsp;cutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assembly is achieved step-wise: First, I glued the 3D printed plastic pieces to the wooden sides of the box, see Fig. 5 (a). Subsequently,
I glued these wooden sides together with painter&amp;#8217;s tape, see Fig. 5 (b), to ensure that everything fits together before doing the final&amp;nbsp;glue-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/assembly_step1_and_step2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/assembly_step1_and_step2.png" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 5: First two steps of assembly process. (a) Plastic pieces are glued to the wooden box sides and pads are attached to
the 3D printed pieces to minimise the slag of the mouse inside the box and to avoid scratches on the mouse.
(b) The wooden box as assembled temporarily with painter&amp;#8217;s tape to ensure proper&amp;nbsp;fitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only after these two steps, I glued the wooden box sides into place with wood glue to achieve a permanently assembled wooden box, see
Fig. 6 (a). Lastly, I applied clear coat to all of the wooden pieces, see Fig. 6&amp;nbsp;(b).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/assembly_step3_and_step4.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/assembly_step3_and_step4.png" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 6: Next two steps of assembly process. (a) The permanent box glue-up with wood glue. (b) Application of liquid clear coat as
finish and to make the box more&amp;nbsp;sturdy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a next step, I prepared the wooden lid for the box using the laser cutter again. Afterwards I cut and glued the leather pieces in place that
attach the lid to the main box body. There are three places that make use of the leather pieces: First, the piece that serves as hinge of the lid, second
the strap to secure the lid to the box with a velcro and lastly another leather piece is placed symmetrically to leather hinge for aesthetic
reasons. Figure 7 shows the finished leather&amp;nbsp;parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/assembly_step5_and_step6.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/assembly_step5_and_step6.png" style="width: 700px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 7: Mouse box with attached leather pieces. (a) Bottom view of the box to see all leather pieces installed. Going from left to right,
the leather pieces serve as closing mechanism of the lid that uses a velcro, hinging mechanism of the lid and aesthetic sugar to the box.
(b) Top view of the box with installed lid and leather&amp;nbsp;pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that, the build is&amp;nbsp;finished!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="final-product"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final&amp;nbsp;product&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finished product is shown in Fig.&amp;nbsp;8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/final_product.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/final_product.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 8: My &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse next to its new custom box. This is what I will use daily in my backpack from now&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, let&amp;#8217;s check out how the mouse itself likes its new box - see Vid.&amp;nbsp;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="560"
            height="315"
            src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j21O3ZNyunM"
            frameborder="0"
            allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
            style="border: 0; margin: 0 auto; display:block; margin-bottom: 10px; max-width: 100%"
            allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
    &lt;p class="caption"&gt;
        Video 3: My mouse checking out its new box. It appears to me that it likes its new&amp;nbsp;accommodation.
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I presented how the open-source 3D scanning software &lt;em&gt;Meshroom&lt;/em&gt; can be used to produce 3D scans without a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt; using
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3D_scanning_colab_notebook.ipynb"&gt;this Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;Google Colab&lt;/em&gt;. Subsequently, I showed how the 3D model can be used for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling.
My demonstration use case was a transportation box for my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; mouse because it is a suitable object to be scanned and used in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps for obtaining a 3D scan that can be used for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling are shown in Fig. 9. While I explain the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt;-specific steps with
&lt;em&gt;Autodesk Fusion 360&lt;/em&gt;, similar steps apply for most &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; software that are on the&amp;nbsp;market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/scanning_pipeline.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/how_to_use_3D_scanning_for_CAD_modeling/scanning_pipeline.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Figure 9: 3D scanning pipeline for obtaining a 3D model that can be used in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly useful is the 3D scanning script for &lt;em&gt;Google Colab&lt;/em&gt; that I provided. With that, you are not required to own a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;-enabled &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; anymore.
Hence, the only thing you need to do to get your own 3D scan is to capture a set of pictures of the object you want to&amp;nbsp;scan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy&amp;nbsp;scanning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="acknowledgments"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Jens Wienkamp for letting me run my first Meshroom experiments on his &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPU&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Internet-capable wooden lamp</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/internet-capable-wooden-lamp.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2019-11-03:/blog/internet-capable-wooden-lamp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I built a wooden lamp around the Sonoff Basic IoT&amp;nbsp;module.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This article describes how I built an internet-capable lamp. The housing and mechanical parts were made with wood working tools, a 3D printer and a laser cutter. The electrical control unit is realised with a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://sonoff.tech/product/wifi-diy-smart-switches/basicr2"&gt;Sonoff Basic&lt;/a&gt; IoT module that can be controlled through an&amp;nbsp;app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-result"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final lamp is shown&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/0_final_result_colorful.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/0_final_result_colorful.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The result of the&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-build-process-in-pictures"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The build process in&amp;nbsp;pictures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following, you can find pictures that document the build process in a top-down approach: the finished product is shown at first and the steps backward in time to arrive at the final product are documented subsequently. The last picture shows the final lamp&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since pictures say more than words, here we go with the&amp;nbsp;pictures:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/1_perspective_painted.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/1_perspective_painted.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The final lamp while it is screwed&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/2_side_view_painted.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/2_side_view_painted.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Side view of the final lamp with the lid slightly displaced to show how the lid attaches to the&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/3_overview_inner.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/3_overview_inner.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Detached lid to show the electrical&amp;nbsp;wiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/4_overview.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/4_overview.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;All parts of the lamp layed out next to each other. The box to the right was made with wood working tools. The remaining wooden pieces were laser cut and most of the white plastic parts were 3D printed from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/5_switch.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/5_switch.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Close up of the 3D printed mechanical switch. A small toggle switch was soldered on a card board and the white 3D printed parts mount around it to provide a mechanism to toggle the switch easily. The small toggle switch is connected in parallel to the existing surface-mounted switch of the Sonoff Basic. The springs provide decent feedback while pressing the&amp;nbsp;switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/6_lampshade_mounting.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/6_lampshade_mounting.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;This laser cut circle is mounted around the bulb housing with metal screws. The remaining six holes provide an interface to attach different lamp shades to the lamp in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/7_bottom_unpainted.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/7_bottom_unpainted.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The wooden base prior to painting. The bottom shows the mounting holes for the 3D printed electronics attachments. The four wider holes on the edges provide a mechanism to attach the&amp;nbsp;lid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/8_mounting_mechanism.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/8_mounting_mechanism.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Close-up of the mounting mechanism of the lid. The wide holes house laser cut wooden pieces with a concentrically aligned M3 nut that has been glued inside these wooden pieces. This way, the lid can be screwed in place, as shown in the second&amp;nbsp;picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/9_electronics_bottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/9_electronics_bottom.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The electronics mounted to the 3D printed pieces, which, themselves, have been screwed inside the unpainted wooden&amp;nbsp;base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/10_electronics_top.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/10_electronics_top.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The 3D printed switch is mounted to the lid and reaches into the inner volume of the lamp. The orange-white cables of the switch will be connected to the Sonoff unit. The green-yellow wires power the actual light bulb and thereby carry mains&amp;nbsp;voltage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/11_perspective_unpainted.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/11_perspective_unpainted.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Assembly of the lamp prior to&amp;nbsp;painting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/12_painting.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/12_painting.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Painting of the wooden base and the lid. The inner sides are spray-painted in&amp;nbsp;black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/13_housing_painted.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/13_housing_painted.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Finished painting of the outside. It is coloured in&amp;nbsp;brown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/14_final_result.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/14_final_result.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The final assembly of the lamp. The power plug goes into the wall and the lamp is connected to the internet via WiFi by using the Sonoff app. After that, it is remotely controllable from anywhere in the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="additional-information-of-the-build"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Additional information of the&amp;nbsp;build&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sonoff Basic is a WiFi-enabled device that is connected in series to the actuator to control. The Sonoff unit comes at a very competitive price point of around $4 and is, if desired, easy to hack to one&amp;#8217;s needs by flasing a custom firmware. Here, however, I decided to stick to the stock firmware for the time being. While that might change later, the firmware it comes with is sufficient for me at this time and it would be easy to change it later&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, the whole exercise of this project is to construct a housing for the Sonoff Basic and to attach a lamp to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I designed the lamp in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; and incorporated parts made from solid wood, 3D printed plastic parts and laser cut wooden parts. Solid wood is used for the outer box to provide sufficient stability for the lamp. 3D printed plastic parts are used for mechanical parts and mountings of the electronics. Laser cut wooden parts are used as decoration and mechanical parts. Last but not least, the electronics is wired to mains&amp;nbsp;voltage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; model is shown below in two&amp;nbsp;visualisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/15_CAD_realistic.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/15_CAD_realistic.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Realistic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; rendering of the 3D model that I drew prior to building the&amp;nbsp;lamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/16_CAD_drawing.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/16_CAD_drawing.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Simpler &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; rendering of the&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual construction is documented above in the preceding section by means of&amp;nbsp;pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wooden lamp around an existing IoT component has been built here. The main features of the lamp&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lamp is not only controllable through an app but there is also a physical switch to trigger it. I made that a key requirement for this lamp project as I wanted to be able to control it by hand as well. The physical switch consists of a 3D printed switch mechanism and a toggle&amp;nbsp;switch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lamp comes with a standard E27 thread for the light bulb. The E27 thread is very popular in Germany as it is used for ceiling lamps so that corresponding light bulbs are easy and cheap to get. I decided to use a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; light bulb for energy and cost&amp;nbsp;efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lamp can be disassembled easily. This way it is easy to, e.g., replace the Sonoff Basic unit or to flash a custom firmware onto it. Furthermore, it is possible to ensure that the mains voltage cable wiring is&amp;nbsp;correct.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mounted a ring with 6 holes to be able to modularly attach a lampshade later&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build process was good fun and I am very happy with the final outcome. It&amp;#8217;s been in use for three weeks now and works reliably: It is a great comfort to be able to control the light from all over the world as well as to control it through the physical switch. In particular, the 3D printed mechanical switch mechanism turns out to work very&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the following picture shows the lamp in its new&amp;nbsp;habitat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/hr/17_lamp_habitat.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/wooden_IoT_lamp/lr/17_lamp_habitat.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;View of how I use the lamp in my&amp;nbsp;room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>3D printed bike lock mount</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3d-printed-bike-lock-mount.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2019-09-01:/blog/3d-printed-bike-lock-mount.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Over are the days of juggling a bike lock while riding my&amp;nbsp;bike!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I like my bike and want to protect it from evil thieves. For that, I use an old solid
lock that comes with the downside of being quite bulky to carry while riding my&amp;nbsp;bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are solutions to this such as putting it in a backpack or holding it in
my hand while riding. But &amp;#8230; where is the fun with these? In particular, when there is
my 3D printer waiting eagerly for jobs. The following figure shows the frame of my bike
from the side. Clearly, there is space for some 3D printed mounting solution&amp;nbsp;:-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/0_picture_of_frame.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/0_picture_of_frame.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Side view of my bike&amp;#8217;s frame. The red arrow indicates available space for
a 3D printed mounting solution for my bike&amp;nbsp;lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the idea in mind to 3D print my prospective bike lock mount, this task becomes
a well-defined engineering question. Hence, I model it digitally as a first&amp;nbsp;step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="modeling-the-problem"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Modeling the&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My bike&amp;#8217;s frame is modeled in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; with &lt;em&gt;Autodesk Fusion 360&lt;/em&gt;. Subsequently, the
same is performed for my old&amp;nbsp;lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I import the above figure into &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ImageJ"&gt;ImageJ&lt;/a&gt;
to determine the angle between the two major rods accurately. This is shown in the following
figure. Second, the bike lock is measured and drawn in 3D as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/1_measuring_angles.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/1_measuring_angles.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Measuring the geometry of my bike&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After modeling the physical system, the fun of designing the bike lock mount itself
begins. Keeping in mind that this design will be 3D printed, I chose a three-part
approach: two identical parts are used as attachments to the frame and the third part
mounts the lock. Without further explaining the design with bare words, please check out
the video below to see how it works in an animation. The white pieces are 3D printed
and metal screws (not shown) are used to hold all pieces&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin: 0px auto; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="650" height="365" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JYmiPLFMNRY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the following figure shows a rendering of the whole setup while being
mounted to the bike&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/2_rendering.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/2_rendering.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Rendering of the designed 3D&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This design is printed on my 3D printer in white &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;. It took around 2x 7h plus 1x 9h, accumulating
to 23h of print time. This long print time arises from the somewhat rigid design and
the very slow print speed that I used. Prior to the design shown in the video above, there existed a
previous design that I did not use due to a failed test print which revealed that it was too bulky.
After the 3D printer finished
with my final design, it was carefully sanded and tested for proper fitting. The following shows
the parts layed out on a&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/3_parts.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/3_parts.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;All parts that are necessary for the assembly. The white parts were 3D printed and the remaining
items are the metal screws and&amp;nbsp;washers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the following two images present a test assembly of the design and verify that not only the
designed parts fit together but also that the lock fits inside. With this, the assembly is ready to be mounted
to the&amp;nbsp;bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/4_half_assembly.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/4_half_assembly.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Half assembled bike lock mount with inserted metal&amp;nbsp;screws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/5_test_assembly.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/5_test_assembly.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Finished test assembly. The lock does fit inside the&amp;nbsp;design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mounting-the-3d-print"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mounting the 3D&amp;nbsp;print&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After cleaning the relevant parts of the bike, the bike lock mount is installed.
First, a rubber band is wrapped around the bike shaft to improve adhesion of
the mount to the bike in azimuthal direction. This can be seen in the following&amp;nbsp;figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/6_rubber.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/6_rubber.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Rubber band wrapped around the bike shaft to increase adhesion of the 3D&amp;nbsp;print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the two identical parts are screwed around the shaft in order to, finally, screw the last 3D
printed piece to the two identical parts. The following two figures show these steps in&amp;nbsp;detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/7_bike_assembly_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/7_bike_assembly_1.jpg" style="height: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The two identical 3D printed pieces are mounted to the&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/8_bike_assembly_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/8_bike_assembly_2.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Subsequently, the last piece is mounted to the pieces installed beforehand and the bike lock
is&amp;nbsp;inserted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, the build is finished and my bike lock mount is safetly mounted to the bike.
Finally, no more dangling around of the&amp;nbsp;lock!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I model a part of my bike in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; and 3D print a plastics mounting assembly for my bike lock.
The assembly has been in use for one week now and everything continues to work&amp;nbsp;great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few lessons have been learned along the&amp;nbsp;way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling for such pieces is incredibly useful. One can avoid improper prototypes
by creating good models, e.g. ensuring that all moving parts will behave as&amp;nbsp;desired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model as much as possible. I forgot to model a minute section of the bike lock which
later required heavy manual post&amp;nbsp;processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no engineering without ideas on how to improve the part. I do not plan to
3D print another version of this design but in case I had to, the following two
improvements would be integrated: (1) A hole inside the housing of the bike lock mount
body in order to drain water and (2) a design that is a little bit less massive. The
latter comes from the fact that I tend to design my functional 3D prints too massive
in their first iteration because I underestimate the strength of 3D printed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t hesitate to contact me via email if you have any questions that remain, I would be very happy
to assist you in a similar process or give extra information about my own experiences. I don&amp;#8217;t provide the model
files of the 3D print here because they are very specific to my particular bike and therefore probably
useless for anybody else. Nevertheless, drop me an email if you would like to get the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; files of
my&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the obligatory evidence of the bike lock mount in wildlife - as found
at places that might be familiar to people from&amp;nbsp;Marburg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/9_evidence_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/9_evidence_1.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The first&amp;nbsp;evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/10_evidence_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/10_evidence_2.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The second&amp;nbsp;evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Turbulence simulation data in real-life</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/turbulence-simulation-data-in-real-life.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-12-19:/blog/turbulence-simulation-data-in-real-life.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;3D print and resin cast of a turbulent flow from 3D simulation&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Amongst others, I developed a code for simulating Newtonian fluids such as water
during my Master studies. Choosing proper settings, one can easily generate large
amounts of 3D data that resembles a turbulent flow in a&amp;nbsp;box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A snapshot of this data was captured and 3D printed. From that, a silicone mould was
made and used to cast a resin version of the simulation&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I am able to hold my abstract experiments from my studies in Theoretical
Physics in my own hands. It took a long way from performing the simulation on a
powerful super computer to creating a real-life silicone mould with which the data
can be&amp;nbsp;casted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps that I performed are the following&amp;nbsp;ones:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate the turbulent data in a channel flow geometry. The boundary conditions
are periodic in spanwise and streamwise directions. The wall-normal direction
uses free-slip boundary&amp;nbsp;conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data is exported to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VTR&lt;/span&gt; format which is read by ParaView. From there,
it is exported as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt;. ParaView is used to find a nice iso surface in the
time&amp;nbsp;series.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The raw simulation data is post-processed in Blender to generate a file
that can be 3D&amp;nbsp;printed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The post-processed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; is 3D&amp;nbsp;printed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The 3D print is sanded and subsequently coated with a fill primer to hide the
3D print specific layer&amp;nbsp;structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A silicone mould is made from the 3D print which is finally used for the resin&amp;nbsp;cast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video visualizes the simulation from which the 3D printed data is taken.
The flow in the simulation box is color
coded where red values are large positive values in the flow  direction and blue values are large negative
values in the flow direction. The flow direction is the x coordinate. The gray surface at t=0 is the one
that is 3D printed and resin casted here. The video shows the turbulent evolution of that surface in&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/videos/turbulentDataCast/turbulence_isosurfaces.mp4"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/turbulence_isosurfaces_frontPic.png" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The simulation data that has been used for the&amp;nbsp;cast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is a mp4 file and can either be downloaded or viewed directly in the&amp;nbsp;browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-outcome"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;outcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, the result of the cast is shown: It is the transparent piece which took
two days to cure inside the silicone&amp;nbsp;mould.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/0_3d_prints.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;3D prints in two sizes, colors and&amp;nbsp;resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/1_mould_box.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;3D print with white fill primer inside its silicone moulding&amp;nbsp;box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/2_silicone_mould.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Silicone&amp;nbsp;mould.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/turbulentDataCast/lr/3_resin_cast.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Resin cast and its&amp;nbsp;template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-details"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is acquired by running the simulation that I wrote for a sufficiently
long time in the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations&amp;#8217; turbulent regime at
Re=400. My simulation is based on a pseudo-spectral algorithm so that one
can reconstruct the full velocity fields from the spectral expansion coefficients
at arbitrary spatial resolutions. The fields are reconstructed and
saved as &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VTR&lt;/span&gt; files (using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/pauloh/pyevtk"&gt;PyEVTK&lt;/a&gt;).
These can be opened in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.paraview.org/"&gt;ParaView&lt;/a&gt; to study how
the fields evolve over time. After deciding upon one flow field and
one of its iso surfaces, the spectral coefficients are used to generate a very
high-resolution spatial field. This data is saved as a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; file is post-processed in Blender: The 2D iso surface is extruded
downwards to obtain a true 3D structure that can be 3D printed. Furthermore,
small artifacts or structures that are hard to 3D print are&amp;nbsp;removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model is 3D printed in black &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;. I tested multiple sizes and multiple vertical resolutions
on an UltiMaker 3. After holding all the 3D prints in my hand I decided to pick
the highest vertical resolution of 0.1mm and a size of 9mm x 6mm x 3mm. This
model is sanded down and white fill primer is applied to hide the vertical layers. It turns out
that this last step reduces the visible vertical layers very well.
That procedure might be an alternative to using an acetone bath for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ABS&lt;/span&gt; in
case &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ABS&lt;/span&gt; cannot be used but a smooth surface is necessary,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A silicone mould is made in a small paper box. Using release spray is recommended
to avoid the destruction of the silicone mould while removing the 3D print. Spending some
time to prepare the 3D print is suggested to polish its look and feel because
the silicone will capture all its details for all the following resin casts to&amp;nbsp;create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This silicone mould is finally used for a resin cast. One can use the silione
mould many times. The casting should be done in a well ventilated room, believe&amp;nbsp;me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="acknowledgements"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ucreatestudio.is.ed.ac.uk/"&gt;uCreate Studio from the University of Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt;  which enabled me to
test multiple prototypes of the 3D print in various sizes and resolutions.
Thanks to their Mike Boyd for ideas on how to realize this project.
This place is truely exceptional and an amazing opportunity for students
to learn anything! I believe the uCreate Studio is a concept that needs to be copied
from universities across the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry></feed>