<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog - Qualitative</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/feeds/qualitative.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://lellep.xyz/blog/</id><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>3D printed bike lock mount</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/3d-printed-bike-lock-mount.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2019-09-01:/blog/3d-printed-bike-lock-mount.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Over are the days of juggling a bike lock while riding my&amp;nbsp;bike!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I like my bike and want to protect it from evil thieves. For that, I use an old solid
lock that comes with the downside of being quite bulky to carry while riding my&amp;nbsp;bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are solutions to this such as putting it in a backpack or holding it in
my hand while riding. But &amp;#8230; where is the fun with these? In particular, when there is
my 3D printer waiting eagerly for jobs. The following figure shows the frame of my bike
from the side. Clearly, there is space for some 3D printed mounting solution&amp;nbsp;:-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/0_picture_of_frame.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/0_picture_of_frame.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Side view of my bike&amp;#8217;s frame. The red arrow indicates available space for
a 3D printed mounting solution for my bike&amp;nbsp;lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the idea in mind to 3D print my prospective bike lock mount, this task becomes
a well-defined engineering question. Hence, I model it digitally as a first&amp;nbsp;step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="modeling-the-problem"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Modeling the&amp;nbsp;problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My bike&amp;#8217;s frame is modeled in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; with &lt;em&gt;Autodesk Fusion 360&lt;/em&gt;. Subsequently, the
same is performed for my old&amp;nbsp;lock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I import the above figure into &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ImageJ"&gt;ImageJ&lt;/a&gt;
to determine the angle between the two major rods accurately. This is shown in the following
figure. Second, the bike lock is measured and drawn in 3D as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/1_measuring_angles.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/1_measuring_angles.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Measuring the geometry of my bike&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After modeling the physical system, the fun of designing the bike lock mount itself
begins. Keeping in mind that this design will be 3D printed, I chose a three-part
approach: two identical parts are used as attachments to the frame and the third part
mounts the lock. Without further explaining the design with bare words, please check out
the video below to see how it works in an animation. The white pieces are 3D printed
and metal screws (not shown) are used to hold all pieces&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin: 0px auto; text-align: center;"&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="650" height="365" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JYmiPLFMNRY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the following figure shows a rendering of the whole setup while being
mounted to the bike&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/2_rendering.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/2_rendering.png" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Rendering of the designed 3D&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This design is printed on my 3D printer in white &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;. It took around 2x 7h plus 1x 9h, accumulating
to 23h of print time. This long print time arises from the somewhat rigid design and
the very slow print speed that I used. Prior to the design shown in the video above, there existed a
previous design that I did not use due to a failed test print which revealed that it was too bulky.
After the 3D printer finished
with my final design, it was carefully sanded and tested for proper fitting. The following shows
the parts layed out on a&amp;nbsp;table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/3_parts.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/3_parts.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;All parts that are necessary for the assembly. The white parts were 3D printed and the remaining
items are the metal screws and&amp;nbsp;washers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the following two images present a test assembly of the design and verify that not only the
designed parts fit together but also that the lock fits inside. With this, the assembly is ready to be mounted
to the&amp;nbsp;bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/4_half_assembly.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/4_half_assembly.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Half assembled bike lock mount with inserted metal&amp;nbsp;screws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/5_test_assembly.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/5_test_assembly.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Finished test assembly. The lock does fit inside the&amp;nbsp;design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mounting-the-3d-print"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mounting the 3D&amp;nbsp;print&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After cleaning the relevant parts of the bike, the bike lock mount is installed.
First, a rubber band is wrapped around the bike shaft to improve adhesion of
the mount to the bike in azimuthal direction. This can be seen in the following&amp;nbsp;figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/6_rubber.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/6_rubber.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Rubber band wrapped around the bike shaft to increase adhesion of the 3D&amp;nbsp;print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the two identical parts are screwed around the shaft in order to, finally, screw the last 3D
printed piece to the two identical parts. The following two figures show these steps in&amp;nbsp;detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/7_bike_assembly_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/7_bike_assembly_1.jpg" style="height: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The two identical 3D printed pieces are mounted to the&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/8_bike_assembly_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/8_bike_assembly_2.jpg" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Subsequently, the last piece is mounted to the pieces installed beforehand and the bike lock
is&amp;nbsp;inserted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, the build is finished and my bike lock mount is safetly mounted to the bike.
Finally, no more dangling around of the&amp;nbsp;lock!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I model a part of my bike in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; and 3D print a plastics mounting assembly for my bike lock.
The assembly has been in use for one week now and everything continues to work&amp;nbsp;great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few lessons have been learned along the&amp;nbsp;way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAD&lt;/span&gt; modeling for such pieces is incredibly useful. One can avoid improper prototypes
by creating good models, e.g. ensuring that all moving parts will behave as&amp;nbsp;desired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model as much as possible. I forgot to model a minute section of the bike lock which
later required heavy manual post&amp;nbsp;processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no engineering without ideas on how to improve the part. I do not plan to
3D print another version of this design but in case I had to, the following two
improvements would be integrated: (1) A hole inside the housing of the bike lock mount
body in order to drain water and (2) a design that is a little bit less massive. The
latter comes from the fact that I tend to design my functional 3D prints too massive
in their first iteration because I underestimate the strength of 3D printed &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PLA&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t hesitate to contact me via email if you have any questions that remain, I would be very happy
to assist you in a similar process or give extra information about my own experiences. I don&amp;#8217;t provide the model
files of the 3D print here because they are very specific to my particular bike and therefore probably
useless for anybody else. Nevertheless, drop me an email if you would like to get the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STL&lt;/span&gt; files of
my&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the obligatory evidence of the bike lock mount in wildlife - as found
at places that might be familiar to people from&amp;nbsp;Marburg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/9_evidence_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/9_evidence_1.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The first&amp;nbsp;evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/hr/10_evidence_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://lellep.xyz/blog/images/bike_lock_mount_3d_print/lr/10_evidence_2.jpg" style="width: 400px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;The second&amp;nbsp;evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="3D Printing"></category></entry><entry><title>Greasing the groove: Push ups - Results</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups-results.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-29T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T23:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-05-29:/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups-results.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Results of 120 push ups for 30&amp;nbsp;days.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did 120 push ups, 6 times 20 repetitions spread arbitrarily over the day, for 30 days
starting the 04/24/2017. The last of these workouts has been done the 23rd of May 2017 without
skipping any repetition during the 30 days. After all, I performed 3600 push&amp;nbsp;ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the 29th of May 2017, I measured my maximal number of push ups anew. Initially, I performed
42 with 20 warming up&amp;nbsp;repetitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time without warming up repetitions, I performed 70 push ups. This is a performance I am
happy&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="experiences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experiences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After approximately 15 days into the challenge, I felt that my handstand and overall
shoulder strength increased. Exercices such as holding a frog position without leaning on my knees
became more accessible and the initial phase of a straddle press felt like I could make future progress
with. In comparison to my pull up challenge of 50 pull ups a day for 30 days in the winter 2015/2016,
this challenge has not had an as big impact on my daily life in terms of soreness and time consumption.
However, also the performance increase hasn&amp;#8217;t been as dramatic. Generally, one should make sure that the
excercise performed in such a challenge is not too difficult as the body will struggle even with the
simplest excercises when repeated that often. While I underestimated that for the past
pull up challenge, I did take this into account for the just finished push up challenge. Getting the 6
sets done over a day was relatively easy so that one could think of performing more than 6 sets. I
did the repetitions exclusively on parallets which (a) protected my wrists and (b) increased the range of
motion. My wrists never made any problems and, amazingly, I got used to the increased range of motion
so that regular flat-hand push ups feel easy now. While the wrists were fine throughout the challenge,
my shoulder felt irritated sometimes. However, never to the degree of pain but mostly only&amp;nbsp;cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="outlook"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various future challanges came to my&amp;nbsp;mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3x 50 push up repetitions a day: For increasing the maximal number. 20 repetitions were too easy
after some&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;L sit to tucked press (explained in terms of the frog position above). I might train these excercises
separately at first to build up enough strength for the&amp;nbsp;challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frog stand on&amp;nbsp;parallets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stretching routine each&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stretching routine seems the most appealing for me now as it is more passive after such an active&amp;nbsp;challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="Sports"></category></entry><entry><title>Greasing the groove: Push ups</title><link href="http://lellep.xyz/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-23T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-04-23T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-04-23:/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Application of &amp;#8220;greasing the groove&amp;#8221; training method to push&amp;nbsp;ups.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I apply the training method &amp;#8220;Greasing the groove&amp;#8221; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#gtg" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; to my push up performance.
My interpretation of this method&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not train the excercise to&amp;nbsp;fatigue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train the excercise very&amp;nbsp;frequently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application to push ups means in this case for&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the maximal performance. Performance is measured as number of
proper-form push ups. To relax my wrists and increase the range of motion, I use my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt;
parallets or knuckles if no parallets are available. &lt;strong&gt;Result&lt;/strong&gt;:
42 push ups after a warm up set of 20&amp;nbsp;repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform half of the maximal performance - 20 in my case at the time being -
six times each day for 30 days. I determined the set number of six by available
time each day, integration in my other physical training and exhaustion. The number of
sets should be distributed equally over the day and are possibly integrated in other training
occasions. The equal distribution includes working times and time at&amp;nbsp;home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this study&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase push up performance. While push ups are an essential excercise, I found
them surprisingly exhausting. I had very good experience with 50 (ring) pull ups
each day for 30 days for my pull up performance in winter&amp;nbsp;2015/2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase overall push performance. This will help for more complex composite movements
that I am weak&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a better push up&amp;nbsp;form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start date is tomorrow, &lt;strong&gt;04/24/2017&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;#8220;We are what we repeatedly do. Excellence, then, is not an act, but a habit.&amp;#8221; (Will Durant)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="gtg" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Further reading can be found here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.100pushups.com/greasing-the-groove/"&gt;http://www.100pushups.com/greasing-the-groove/&lt;/a&gt;.
No guarantee on correctness but a good read.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="Sports"></category></entry></feed>