<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Blog - sports</title><link href="https://lellep.xyz/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://lellep.xyz/blog/feeds/sports.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://lellep.xyz/blog/</id><updated>2023-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><subtitle>by Martin Lellep</subtitle><entry><title>Habit self-experiment: 6 months of daily stretching</title><link href="https://lellep.xyz/blog/habit-six-months-of-daily-stretching.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2023-01-01:/blog/habit-six-months-of-daily-stretching.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;I used an app to capture my daily streching for 6 months and present the quantitative results in form of a&amp;nbsp;figure.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discussion:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/flexibility/comments/100hlzn/selfexperiment_6_months_of_daily_deep_squatting"&gt;on Reddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to improve my flexibility, I did deep squats and sitting cross legged daily in the last half of 2022. I used the open source phone app &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.isoron.uhabits&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=US"&gt;Loop Habit Tracker&lt;/a&gt;, which I can recommend as this made the whole undertaking quite easy to track and exporting the full data was also&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the time spent in the two exercises against time in the year in the figure below. On average, I did 5min of deep squatting and around 3min of sitting cross legged. Those times were picked so that they could be done in-between other tasks&amp;nbsp;easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://lellep.xyz/blog/images/six_months_of_daily_stretching/increasing_flexibility_with_habbits.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://lellep.xyz/blog/images/six_months_of_daily_stretching/increasing_flexibility_with_habbits.jpg" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My personal experience&lt;/strong&gt; is that I made good progress with sitting cross legged but somewhat stagnated with my deep squat progress. I was relatively good with the latter to begin with and probably should have altered my routine after some weeks to make better&amp;nbsp;progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General learning:&lt;/strong&gt; Based on this experiment, I conclude that sticking to one stretching exercise for 4 to 8 weeks is enough. After that period, I will alter my routine in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created the images of the exercises in the above figure using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stable_Diffusion"&gt;Stable Diffusion&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/GIMP"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIMP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="sports"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="habits"></category></entry><entry><title>Greasing the groove: Push ups - Results</title><link href="https://lellep.xyz/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups-results.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-29T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T23:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-05-29:/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups-results.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Results of 120 push ups for 30&amp;nbsp;days.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I did 120 push ups, 6 times 20 repetitions spread arbitrarily over the day, for 30 days
starting the 04/24/2017. The last of these workouts has been done the 23rd of May 2017 without
skipping any repetition during the 30 days. After all, I performed 3600 push&amp;nbsp;ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the 29th of May 2017, I measured my maximal number of push ups anew. Initially, I performed
42 with 20 warming up&amp;nbsp;repetitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time without warming up repetitions, I performed 70 push ups. This is a performance I am
happy&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="experiences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experiences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After approximately 15 days into the challenge, I felt that my handstand and overall
shoulder strength increased. Exercices such as holding a frog position without leaning on my knees
became more accessible and the initial phase of a straddle press felt like I could make future progress
with. In comparison to my pull up challenge of 50 pull ups a day for 30 days in the winter 2015/2016,
this challenge has not had an as big impact on my daily life in terms of soreness and time consumption.
However, also the performance increase hasn&amp;#8217;t been as dramatic. Generally, one should make sure that the
excercise performed in such a challenge is not too difficult as the body will struggle even with the
simplest excercises when repeated that often. While I underestimated that for the past
pull up challenge, I did take this into account for the just finished push up challenge. Getting the 6
sets done over a day was relatively easy so that one could think of performing more than 6 sets. I
did the repetitions exclusively on parallets which (a) protected my wrists and (b) increased the range of
motion. My wrists never made any problems and, amazingly, I got used to the increased range of motion
so that regular flat-hand push ups feel easy now. While the wrists were fine throughout the challenge,
my shoulder felt irritated sometimes. However, never to the degree of pain but mostly only&amp;nbsp;cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="outlook"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Outlook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various future challanges came to my&amp;nbsp;mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3x 50 push up repetitions a day: For increasing the maximal number. 20 repetitions were too easy
after some&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;L sit to tucked press (explained in terms of the frog position above). I might train these excercises
separately at first to build up enough strength for the&amp;nbsp;challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frog stand on&amp;nbsp;parallets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stretching routine each&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stretching routine seems the most appealing for me now as it is more passive after such an active&amp;nbsp;challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="sports"></category></entry><entry><title>Greasing the groove: Push ups</title><link href="https://lellep.xyz/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-23T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-04-23T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Martin Lellep</name></author><id>tag:lellep.xyz,2017-04-23:/blog/greasing-the-groove-push-ups.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Application of &amp;#8220;greasing the groove&amp;#8221; training method to push&amp;nbsp;ups.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I apply the training method &amp;#8220;Greasing the groove&amp;#8221; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#gtg" id="footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; to my push up performance.
My interpretation of this method&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not train the excercise to&amp;nbsp;fatigue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train the excercise very&amp;nbsp;frequently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application to push ups means in this case for&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the maximal performance. Performance is measured as number of
proper-form push ups. To relax my wrists and increase the range of motion, I use my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DIY&lt;/span&gt;
parallets or knuckles if no parallets are available. &lt;strong&gt;Result&lt;/strong&gt;:
42 push ups after a warm up set of 20&amp;nbsp;repetitions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform half of the maximal performance - 20 in my case at the time being -
six times each day for 30 days. I determined the set number of six by available
time each day, integration in my other physical training and exhaustion. The number of
sets should be distributed equally over the day and are possibly integrated in other training
occasions. The equal distribution includes working times and time at&amp;nbsp;home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this study&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase push up performance. While push ups are an essential excercise, I found
them surprisingly exhausting. I had very good experience with 50 (ring) pull ups
each day for 30 days for my pull up performance in winter&amp;nbsp;2015/2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase overall push performance. This will help for more complex composite movements
that I am weak&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a better push up&amp;nbsp;form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start date is tomorrow, &lt;strong&gt;04/24/2017&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;#8220;We are what we repeatedly do. Excellence, then, is not an act, but a habit.&amp;#8221; (Will Durant)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="gtg" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#footnote-reference-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Further reading can be found here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.100pushups.com/greasing-the-groove/"&gt;http://www.100pushups.com/greasing-the-groove/&lt;/a&gt;.
No guarantee on correctness but a good read.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content><category term="sports"></category></entry></feed>